<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Private devotions digested into six letanies; I. Of confession. II. Of deprecation. III. Of supplication. IV. Of Thanksgiving. V. Of intercession. VI. For the sick. VVith directions and prayers for the Lords day. Sacrament. day of Death. Judgment. And two daily prayers, one for the morning, another for the evening.</title>
            <author>Valentine, Henry, d. 1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 194 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64846</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V23B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219631</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831087</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831087</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35549</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64846)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35549)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2084:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Private devotions digested into six letanies; I. Of confession. II. Of deprecation. III. Of supplication. IV. Of Thanksgiving. V. Of intercession. VI. For the sick. VVith directions and prayers for the Lords day. Sacrament. day of Death. Judgment. And two daily prayers, one for the morning, another for the evening.</title>
                  <author>Valentine, Henry, d. 1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The thirteenth edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[8], 377, [1] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for H. Moseley at the Princes Arms in S. Pauls Church yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Henry Valentine.</note>
                  <note>A1v = verse; A2v = frontis.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devotional exercises --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:35549:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Behold this Publican, i'th Temple praying;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Plac'd in the front, as of our book beginner:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The form of whoſe devotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was this ſaying,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O Lord be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God heard his ſuit; though ſhort, 'tis not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni'd:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He came a ſinner, but went juſtify'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:35549:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35549:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Penitent publican at prayer in entrance to a church</figDesc>
                  <head>Priuate DEVOTIONS</head>
                  <p>Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> mercifull to me a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London Printed for Geo: Badger and are to bee ſould at his shopp at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Dunſtons-Churchyard in fleetstreet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35549:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PRIVATE DEVOTIONS, <hi>Digeſted into</hi> SIX LETANIES;
<list>
                  <item>I. Of Confeſſion.</item>
                  <item>II. Of Deprecation.</item>
                  <item>III. Of Supplication.</item>
                  <item>IV. Of Thankſgiving.</item>
                  <item>V. Of Interceſſion.</item>
                  <item>VI. For the Sick.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVith Directions and Prayers</hi> For the
<list>
                  <item>Lords Day.</item>
                  <item>Sacrament.</item>
                  <item>day of
<list>
                        <item>Death.</item>
                        <item>Judgment.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And two daily Prayers,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>One for the Morning.</item>
                  <item>Another for the Evening.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The thirteenth Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Moſeley</hi> at the Princes Arms in <hi>S. Pauls</hi> Church yard, 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:35549:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35549:3"/>
            <head>To the right Honorable, THOMAS Lo: COVENTRY, Baron of <hi>Ailesborough,</hi> and Lord Keeper of the great Seale of <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My good Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Law permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a man that was not able to bring a lamb to the Altar, to offer a pair of Turtle Doves, or two young Pigeons.</p>
            <p>The Goſpel commends Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in a cup of cold water; &amp; magnifies the devotion &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the widow that caſt in <hi>2</hi> mites into the Treaſury.</p>
            <p>I muſt ever acknowledge,
<pb facs="tcp:35549:4"/>that mine obligation to your Lordſhip might challenge a volume; but wanting that, I have preſumed to preſent you with this Manuall, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiridion of private Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the love and exerciſe whereof hath advanced your Lordſhip to publike honour. It is but a little one, yet ſince it was firſt preſented to your hands, it hath ſo thriven by your Lordſhips patronage, that it hath had many Editions &amp; Additions. And I am glad of it, for the bigger it grows, the better proportion it will carry with his ſervice that is </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ever devoted to <hi>Your Lo<hi rend="sup">p</hi> in all Duty,</hi> Henry Valentine.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35549:4"/>
            <head>ORATIO</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Deo Sacrificium.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oranti ſubſidium.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Daemonibus flagellum.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>That is, <hi>PRAYER IS</hi> a
<list>
                  <item>Sacrifice to God.</item>
                  <item>Succour to the ſoule.</item>
                  <item>Scourge to the divel.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Praier is
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Clavis Diei.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sera Noctis.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>A Key to open the Morning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My voice ſhalt thou heare in the morning.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:35549:5"/>
            <p>O Lord, in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning will I direct my prayer unto thee, and will look up. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.3.</p>
            <p>Unto thee have I cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ô Lord, and in the Morning ſhall my prayer prevent thee. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.13.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>A lock to ſhut up the Evening.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At Evening will I pray, and cry aloud, and he ſhall hear my voice. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 55.17.</p>
            <p>Let my prayer be ſet forth before thee as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe: and the lifting up
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35549:5"/>of mine hands as the eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſacrifice. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 141.2.</p>
            <p>Morning and Evening.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aaron</hi> ſhall burn ſweet incenſe every morning. And when he lighteth the Lamps at Even, he ſhall burn ſweet incenſe. <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.7, 8.</p>
            <p>In the Morning ſow thy ſeed, and in the Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with-hold not thine hand: for thou knoweſt not whether ſhall proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, either this or that, or whether they both ſhall be alike good. <hi>Ecc.</hi> 11.6.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:35549:6"/>
               <head>I. CONFESSION OF SINNES.</head>
               <p>COnfeſsion is a branch of praier, which ſearches out our ſins, and diſcloſes and ſpreads them open before the Lord, as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> did thoſe letters which he received from the King of Aſſyria: or as <hi>Joſuah</hi> opened the cave of Makkedah, and brought out the five Kings that were there hidden; ſo this opens the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35549:6"/>heart and brings out our hidden and boſome ſins to light and execution. And as the opening of a vein rectifies the diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the body, ſo this cures the maladies of the ſoul: for if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our ſinnes, God is faithfull and juſt to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us our ſins, and to cleanſe us from all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs. In a word, it is commanded by God, and practiſed by the Saints, and <hi>Solomon</hi> makes it the character of a righteous man, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35549:7"/>himſelf in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his praier. A man dreames when he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, but cannot declare his dream till he awake. Confeſſion is a ſign that we are awakned from the ſleep of ſin by the grace of God.</p>
               <p>I ſaid, I will confeſſe my tranſgreſsions to the Lord, and thou forga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt the iniquity of my ſin. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.5.</p>
               <p>I have not covered my tranſgreſsions as Adam; by hiding mine iniquity in my boſome. <hi>Job</hi> 31.33.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:35549:7"/>
               <p>But I acknowledge my tranſgreſsions, and my ſin is ever before me. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.3.</p>
               <div type="litany">
                  <head>THE LETANY of Confeſsion.</head>
                  <p>BEhold, I was ſhapen in wickedneſs, and in ſin hath my mother con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When I was a childe I ſpake as a childe, I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood as a childe, I thought as a child, and as yet have not put away
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35549:8"/>childiſh things from me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When I grew up, the luſts of the fleſh grew too ſtrong for me, they fought againſt me, and prevailed; the cares of the world diſtracted me, the pleaſures of the world deceived me, the pride of life ſwelled me, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of revenge inflamed me, and ſin reigned in my mortal body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have given up the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35549:8"/>members of my body as weapons of ſin, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: my head to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine miſchief, my hands to work wickedneſs, my tongue to ſwearing and blaſphemy, my eares to filthy and corrupt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, my eyes to behold vanity, my feet to ſtand in the way of ſinners, and to walk in the counſell of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly; ſo that from the crown of the head, to the ſole of the foot, there is no ſound part in me.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:35549:9"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have either omitted good duties, or done them ſlightly and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily: I have neglected the time of my viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I have not known in my day the things that belong to my peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have offended thee, and treſpaſſed my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by my improvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and raſhneſſe, by my anger and intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſpeech; by my wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35549:9"/>envy, malice and uncharitableneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have ſinned in all them whom I have cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by my words, counſel, or example: in all them whom I ſhould have reproved, whom I might have reformed, and did not.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have ſinned in neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting opportunities to viſit the houſe and table of the Lord, in unworthy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35549:10"/>and unprepared reſort thither, in wandring and idle thoughts there, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diverting me from the work of thy holy worſhip, or diſtracting me in it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have ſinned in unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent and unprofitable hearing thy Word, in cold and careleſs invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of thy Name, without zeale and holy affection, which turned my prayers into ſin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:35549:11"/>
                  <p>I have ſinned by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull paſſing over thy many good favours, by ſlighting them with an unhearty commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſo that my ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of praiſe became the ſacrifice of fools.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have broken all my vows and purpoſes, I have not kept my ſolemn promiſes of forſaking my ſin, &amp; amending my life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have delaied my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35549:12"/>I have reſiſted the checks of mine own conſcience, I have quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the motions of thy Spirit, I have put off the good works, whereby I might have glorified thee, bettered my ſelf, &amp; benefited my neighbour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have corrupted the beſt of my thoughts, words, works, and ways, by cheriſhing the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of mine own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by entertaining the ſecret temptations of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35549:12"/>and the open intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the wicked world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have been an evill husband of the talent of grace which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to my improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I have been an unthrift of that time which was lent me for repentance, and the work of my ſalvation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have belied my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt heart with fair ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35549:13"/>of goodneſs, and have hypocritically deceived the good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of charity which beleeveth the beſt; I have boaſted in the praiſe that I deſerved not, to thy offence, who requireſt truth in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have overweened the meaſure of grace in my ſelf, &amp; corrupted it with my pride: I have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued the goodneſs of my neighbour, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35549:13"/>have leſſened it with abatements, or depraved it with unjuſt imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have heard and ſeen thee my God diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, my neighbour tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and wronged, &amp; I have done right to nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but either for fear of offence, for partial af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, for baſe flattery, or ungodly modeſty, or for uncharitable envy I have forborn to ariſe in their juſt defence.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:35549:14"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have not alwayes ſought the outward bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of life by good meanes, ſanctified by prayer: I have not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes received them with thankſgiving and contentedneſſe: I have not alwayes uſed them with ſobriety, nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed the over-meaſure with the piety and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that I ought.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have not uſed my
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35549:14"/>lawful pleaſures ſo ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably, ſo moderately, ſo religiouſly, ſo thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully as I ought, but I have offended thee my God in my mirth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have not ſought peace with all men, nor always imbraced it when it hath been offered: I have not loved mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, nor bleſſed him that curſed me, nor done good to him that meant or did me hurt: I have not given him ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35549:15"/>as I begged from thee for my ſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have ſinned in vaine thoughts, in vaſt deſires, in ungodly hopes, in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſte dreams, in ſecret covetings of the goods or delights of my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have ſinned in the unconſcionable practice of theſe ſins without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe or repentance, or if any good motions of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35549:15"/>thy Spirit have bred in me a godly ſorrow for them, the next temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath either replaſed me into the old, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plunged mee in ſome new ſin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have hid ſome of theſe ſins as Adam, ſome of them I have excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with pretences, ſome I have denied againſt the teſtimony of my accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing conſcience, ſome I have wickedly maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, none I have through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35549:16"/>repented &amp; amended.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have committed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſecret ſins that I have not been aware of: I have ſinned in the beſt of my works, and intentions of piety and charity, even when I moſt laboured to doe thee ſervice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have ſinned all theſe wayes, and done many evils that I have forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, many that I have paſt over without conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35549:16"/>and repentance: and now what ſhall I do to thee, O thou preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of men, and Judge of the whole world?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lord be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Have mercy upon me O Lord, according to thy loving kindneſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the multitude of thy tender compaſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons blot out all my of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences. <hi>Amen. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, in whoſe moſt bleſſed name and words, we conclude theſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35549:17"/>our imperfect prayers, ſaying as he himſelf hath taught us:</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="Pater_Noster">
                     <body>
                        <p>OUR Father which art in heaven, Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed be thy name. Thy Kingdome come. Thy will be done in earth as it is in heaven. Give us this day our daily bread. And forgive us our treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, as we forgive them that treſpaſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us. And lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil. For thine is the Kingdome, the power, and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35549:17"/>for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <head>Morning Prayer.</head>
                        <p>OLord our heavenly Father, almighty &amp; everlaſting God, which haſt ſafely brought us to the beginning of this day, defend us in the ſame with thy mighty power, and grant that this day we fall into no ſin, neither run into any kinde of danger, but that all our doings may be ordered by thy gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to do always that is righteous in thy ſight,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35549:18"/>through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <head>Evening Prayer.</head>
                        <p>LIghten our darkneſſe, we beſeech thee, O Lord, and by thy great mercy defend us from all perils and dangers of this night, for the love of thy onely Son our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <p>THe grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the love of God, and the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the holy Ghoſt, be with us all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:35549:18"/>
               <head>II. DEPRECATION.</head>
               <p>DEprecation is a branch of prayer directed to God, either for the averſion and prevention of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill before it comes, or for the removing and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it away when it is come. And the evil w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> we deprecate may be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the evill of ſin, or the evill of puniſhment. When we either feel or fear an evil, we muſt not with <hi>Eliah</hi> or <hi>Jonah</hi> ſit
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35549:19"/>down, and in a ſullen hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour wiſh our ſelves out of the world, but we muſt pray as Chriſt did for his Diſciples, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.15. not that he would take us out of the world, but that he would keep us from the evil. And ſo doing, we have Gods promiſe not to be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted above our ſtrength. For either he will abate the croſſe, or increaſe our ſtrength to bear it; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he will remove the temptation, or give us his grace, which is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for us.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:35549:19"/>
               <p>Deliver us from evil <hi>Luke</hi> 11.4.</p>
               <p>Deliver me from all my tranſgreſſions.</p>
               <p>Make me not the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the fooliſh. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.</p>
               <p>Remove thy ſtroke from me.</p>
               <p>Deliver my ſoul from the ſword: my darling from the dog.</p>
               <p>Save me from the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons mouth, from the horns of the Unicorns. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.20, 21.</p>
               <div type="litany">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:35549:20"/>
                  <head>THE LETANY of Deprecation.</head>
                  <p>FRom all the ſinnes that I have done, and from all that I would have done, if thy grace had not prevented and reſtrained me,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From my cloſe &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſins, and from thoſe ſins to which I am incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by nature, or inticed by company, or allured by pleaſure and profit, or drawn by the example of this evil world,</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:35549:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From all the ſins that I have felt in my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and confeſſed with my mouth, and bewailed with my heart, and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged pardon of thee with my tongue,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From all the ſecret &amp; unknown ſins which my conſcience hath not felt, nor my mouth confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, nor my heart bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, nor my tongue beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged pardon,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From the whole cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35549:21"/>of my nature; from all the temptations of the Divel, from the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements of the world, from the luſts of the fleſh and eyes,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From all vanity of minde, dulneſs of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, perverſneſſe of will, crookedneſs of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, deadneſs &amp; hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart, and from a benummed, blinded, or ſeared conſcience,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From all wandring imaginations, from all
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35549:21"/>looſneſs of deſires, from all tranſgreſſions of thy holy and juſt command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and from the firſt motions to any ſin againſt thee or my neighbour,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From relapſing into the ſins that I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, from turning thy grace into wantonneſſe, from treading under foot the bloud of thy cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, from neglect and contempt of the meanes of ſalvation,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From all ſchiſm &amp; he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35549:22"/>from infidelity and apoſtaſie, &amp; from the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From famine &amp; ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, from plague and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, and from all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy ſore and heavy judgements, at this time and ever hereafter,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From poverty and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme neceſsity, from ſickneſs and diſeaſes in my body, from grief and vexation of mind, from loſſe of liberty, goods, or friends, from blemiſh and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35549:22"/>ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dal of my good name</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From giving offence unadviſedly, and from taking offence unjuſtly,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From thy wrath and indignation, from final deſpair of thy grace and pardon, and from ſudden death,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From the ſentence of condemnation, from the Lake of brimſtone, from the chains of everlaſting darkneſs, from the worm that dies not, and the fire
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35549:23"/>that ſhall never be quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O Lord I beſeech thee deliver my ſoul. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.4. <hi>Amen. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, in whoſe moſt bleſſed name and words we conclude theſe our imperfect prayers, ſaying as he himſelf hath taught us:</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <p>OUR Father which art in heaven, &amp;c.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <head>Morning Prayer.</head>
                        <p>O Lord our heavenly Father, almighty &amp;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35549:23"/>everlaſting God, which haſt ſafely brought us to the beginning of this day, defend us in the ſame with thy mighty power, &amp; grant that this day we fall into no ſin, neither run into any kind of danger, but that all our doings may be orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by thy governance, to doe alwayes that is righteous in thy ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <head>Evening Prayer.</head>
                        <p>LIghten our darkneſs, we beſeech thee, O
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35549:24"/>Lord, and by thy great mercy defend us from all perils and dangers of this night, for the love of thy only Son our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <p>THE grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the love of God, and the fellowſhip of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, be with us all evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III. SUPPLICATION.</head>
               <p>SUpplication is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther branch of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, whereby we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of God that hee
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35549:24"/>would give us ſuch bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings as we want, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue and inlarge ſuch bleſsings as we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. And theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings are either corporal or ſpiritual, temporal or eternal. For ſuch bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings as are ſpiritual and acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany ſalvation, pray for them in the firſt place; Firſt ſeek the Kingdom of God &amp; the righteuoſneſs thereof; &amp; we may pray for them abſolutely: for the other we muſt pray conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, with a reference &amp;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35549:25"/>ſubmiſſion of our will to Gods will, who beſt knows what is good for us. Not my will, but thine be done. Thy will be done in earth as it is in heaven.</p>
               <p>O Thou that heareſt prayer, unto thee ſhall all fleſh come, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.2.</p>
               <p>Lord hear my voice, let thine eares be atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to my ſupplications. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.2.</p>
               <p>Behold now that I have taken upon me to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35549:25"/>ſpeak to the Lord, who am but duſt and aſhes: O let not the Lord bee angry, and I will ſpeak.</p>
               <div type="litany">
                  <head>THE LETANY of Supplication.</head>
                  <p>THat it may pleafe thee to fill mine heart and my mouth with thy praiſe all my life long, for all thy faithfulneſſe, and truth, and loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhewed to me in the land of the living.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:35549:26"/>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to give me a clear judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſee my ſins, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affections to hate and abhorre them, true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to bewail and forſake them, with a ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt purpoſe and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt them for the time to come.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to waſh mee throwly from mine iniquities, and to cleanſe me from my ſins, that I may be whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then ſnow.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:35549:26"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to apply to my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the obedience of the life, and the ſacrifice of the death of Jeſus Chriſt for the aſſurance of thy favour, and my pardon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to create in me a clean heart, to renew a right ſpirit within me, to give me truth in my inward parts, and to eſtabliſh me with thy free Spirit.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:35549:27"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to give me ſuch graces as I want, and to increaſe thoſe which I have, that I may grow fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrength to ſtrength, till I become a perfect man.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to make me an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy glory, &amp; to direct all my thoughts, words, &amp; works, for the inlargement &amp; advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy Kingdome.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:35549:27"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to eſtabliſh in mee the Kingdome of thy power to rule and awe me; and the Kingdome of thy grace to ſanctifie me to the knowledge, love, and obedience of thy will.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to enable me to doe thy will with chearfulneſs &amp; alacrity, with perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and conſtancy, as thy bleſſed Angels and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35549:28"/>Saints in heaven do it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to open thy full hand, &amp; to beſtow upon me the neceſſaries of this life, &amp; the fruits of the earth in due ſeaſon, with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of health, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to give me thy bleſsing with them: that I may uſe them wiſely, ſoberly, juſtly, charitably, thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35549:28"/>and contentedly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to bleſſe me in all the works of my calling with grace and ſtrength, to obtain, to keep, and to uſe a good conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee &amp; my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to my lives end.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to ſanctifie my life, to ſweeten my death, and to raiſe up my body in the day of the Lo: Jeſus.</p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:35549:29"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finally, that it may pleaſe thee to give me my maſters joy, my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers inheritance, the Crown of righteouſneſs, the glory of the new Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, &amp; to ſatisfie me with that fulneſs of joy which is in thy preſence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O Lord hear my prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and let my cry come unto thee. <hi>Amen. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, in whoſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:35549:29"/>moſt bleſſed name and words, we conclude theſe our imperfect prayers, ſaying as he himſelf hath taught us:</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <p>Our Father which art art in heaven, &amp;c.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <head>Morning Prayer.</head>
                        <p>O Lord our heavenly Father, almighty &amp; everlaſting God, which haſt ſafely brought us to the beginning of this day, defend us in the ſame with thy mighty power, &amp; grant that this day we fall into no ſin, neither run into any kind
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35549:30"/>of danger, but that all our doings may be orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by thy governance, to doe alwayes that is righteous in thy ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <head>Evening Prayer.</head>
                        <p>LIghten our darkneſs, we beſeech thee, O Lord, and by thy great mercy defend us from all perils and dangers of this night, for the love of thy only Son our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:35549:30"/>
                        <p>THE grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the love of God, and the fellowſhip of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, be with us all evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV. THANKSGIVING.</head>
               <p>Thankſgiving is a branch of praier, which, like the Leper in the Goſpell, turns back to God with a confeſsion and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath done for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And it is ſo neceſſary and eſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall a part of Gods wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:35549:31"/>that it is the very condition of the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein God hath bound himſelf by his promiſe to hear us. Call upon me in the day of trouble, and I will deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thee, and thou ſhalt praiſe me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. ſo that if we praiſe him not, we break the Covenant, and are uſurpers upon all his bleſſings and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances.</p>
               <p>Thy loving kindneſs is better then life: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my lips ſhall praiſe thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.3, 4.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:35549:31"/>
               <p>Thus will I magnifie thee al my life; and lift up my hands in thy Name.</p>
               <p>Seven times a day do I praiſe thee, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.164.</p>
               <p>My mouth ſhall ſhew forth thy righteouſneſſe and thy ſalvation all the day long: for I know no end thereof, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 71.15.</p>
               <p>While I live I will praiſe the Lord, I will ſing praiſes to my God while I have any being, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.2.</p>
               <p>Bleſſe the Lord, O my ſoul; and forget not all
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35549:32"/>his benefits, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.2</p>
               <p>O Lord open thou my lips, and my mouth ſhall ſhew forth thy praiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.15.</p>
               <div type="litany">
                  <head>THE LETANY of Thankſgiving.</head>
                  <p>FOR the grace of Election, by which I was choſen ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the good pleaſure of thy will</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoule doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the grace of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, by which I was made after thine image
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35549:32"/>in righteouſneſſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoule doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the grace of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, by which I was recovered from the guilt &amp; dominion of ſin, from the power of Satan, and the ſecond death,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the grace of Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wrought in me by the inward working of thy Spirit, &amp; the outward miniſtry of thy holy Word and Sacraments,</p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:35549:33"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the grace of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, whereby I am clothed with the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt Jeſus</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For my meaſure of Sanctification, by which I am made a new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For my formation in the womb, my birth, my baptiſme, the illuminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my underſtanding,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35549:33"/>the correction of my will, and all the ſpiritual graces received fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the liberty of thy Word and Sacraments, for thy ſanctuary and ſolemne aſſemblies, and for thy gracious preſence with us in them</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For thy conſtant pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in ſupplying my neceſsities, and defending me from dangers</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:35549:34"/>
                  <p>For my good parents, my education, my health liberty, and peace, for the comfort of my friends, for my daily bread, and for all thy temporall bleſsings</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For thy prevention of evils, ſubvention in evils, &amp; deliverance from evil</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For thy patience in forbearing, for thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in forgiving, for thy bounty in giving, even
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35549:34"/>when I ſinned againſt thee with a high hand</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For my life, and the ſeaſon given me for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance &amp; good works, and for thy holy means of grace and ſalvation</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the checks of mine own conſcience, for the inſtruction of thy word, for the motions of thy good Spirit which have either reſtrained me from ſin, or cauſed
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35549:35"/>me to repent of it</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For thy fatherly corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions by ſome ſpirituall conflicts with Satan, by diſeaſes, or hurts in my body, by griefs of mind, loſſe of goods, moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of injuries, diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts for, or from thoſe to whom naturall, civil, or Chriſtian acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance had indeared me</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For all the holy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs and Prophets
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:35549:35"/>for the ever bleſſed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord, for all the holy Apoſtles and Evangeliſts, for all the godly Biſhops and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of the Church, for all the noble Army of Martyrs, and Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and for all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that have lived and died in the Lord</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the happy tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Saints depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in peace, from this vale of tears to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of the juſt</p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:35549:36"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For thine holy Angels; and the charge which thou haſt given them to miniſter unto us, to pitch their tents about us, to keep us in all our ways, and to convey our ſouls into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For Jeſus Chriſt the author and finiſher of our faith, and the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and foundation of all theſe favours;</p>
                  <p>For his conception &amp; birth;</p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:35549:36"/>
                  <p>For his circumciſion and baptiſm;</p>
                  <p>For his faſting and temptation;</p>
                  <p>For his doctrine and miracles;</p>
                  <p>For his agony and bloody ſweat;</p>
                  <p>For his croſs &amp; paſsion;</p>
                  <p>For his death &amp; burial;</p>
                  <p>For his victorious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion into hell;</p>
                  <p>For his glorious reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and aſcenſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heaven;</p>
                  <p>For his ſitting at the right hand of God to make interceſsion always for us;</p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:35549:37"/>
                  <p>For his ſending the holy Ghoſt to a bide with his Church for ever, and for his being with us to the end of the world</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For thy bleſſed Spirit the enlightner of my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of my will, the helper of my infirmities, the comforter of my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the pledge and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my adoption, and the ſeal of my ſalvation</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:35549:37"/>
                  <p>For all my perſonall &amp; particular deliverances; for the religion, peace, plenty, ſtrength, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the State where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I live; for ſaving it all times, eſpecially from the Spaniſh invaſion, and the Popiſh powder treaſon</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For all the ſecret fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours which thou haſt done for us, for all the mercies which we have received from thee, and are ſlipt out of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, and for all
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:35549:38"/>the goodneſs which thou haſt laid up for them that fear thee, and love thy coming</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie thee O Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What ſhall I render to the Lord for all his benefits towards me?</p>
                  <p>I will take the cup of ſalvation and call upon the Name of the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.12.</p>
                  <p>I will ſing of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Lord for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: with my mouth wil I make known thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to all generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 89.1.</p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:35549:38"/>
                  <p>Let them that fear the Lord, ſay alwayes, The Lord be praiſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As it was in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, is now, and ever ſhal be, world without end.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amen. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, in whoſe moſt bleſſed name and words we conclude theſe our imperfect prayers, ſaying as he himſelf hath taught us:</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="70" facs="tcp:35549:39"/>
                        <p>OUR Father which art in heaven, &amp;c.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <head>Morning Prayer.</head>
                        <p>OLord our heavenly Father, almighty &amp; everlaſting God, which haſt ſafely brought us to the beginning of this day, defend us in the ſame with thy mighty power, &amp; grant that this day we fall into no ſin, neither run into any kind of danger, but that all our doings may be orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by thy governance, to doe alwayes that is righteous in thy ſight,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:35549:39"/>through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <head>Evening Prayer.</head>
                        <p>LIghten our darkneſs, we beſeech thee, O Lord, and by thy great mercy defend us from all perils and dangers of this night, for the love of thy onely Son our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <p>THe grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the love of God, and the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the holy Ghoſt, be with us all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:35549:40"/>
               <head>V. INTERCESSION.</head>
               <p>INterceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is abranch of prayer, extending and inlarging our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires for others: as we ſee in <hi>Abraham,</hi> who interce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Maſes</hi> for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> for <hi>Saul.</hi> And this duty is very acceptable to God for neceſsity conſtrains us to pray for our ſelves, but charity moves us to become petitioners for others. And the prayer of charity is more acceptable to God, then
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:35549:40"/>the prayer of neceſsity. Again, it is very profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for us; for though our prayers ſhould not profit them, yet they will profit us; for they ſhall be turned into our own boſomes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Si pro te tantum roges, pro te tantum rogabis: Si autem pro omnibus roges, pro te omnes rog abunt.</hi> Amb. l. 1. de Cain, &amp;c. cap. 1.</p>
               <p>I exhort therefore that firſt of all ſupplication, prayers, interceſsions, &amp; giving of thanks bee made for all men; for this
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:35549:41"/>is good and acceptable in the ſight of God our Saviour, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, 3.</p>
               <p>And pray always with all manner of prayer and ſupplication in the ſpirit: and watch thereunto with all perſeverance and ſupplication for all Saints. And for me, that utterance may be given unto me, that I may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen my mouth boldly to publiſh the ſecret of the Goſpel. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.18, 19.</p>
               <p>Is any ſick among you? let him call for the Elders of the Church,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:35549:41"/>and let them pray over him. And the prayer of faith ſhall ſave the ſick, and the Lord ſhall raiſe him up, and if he have committed ſinnes, they ſhall be forgiven him, <hi>James</hi> 5.14, 15.</p>
               <p>But as for me, when they were ſick my clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was ſackcloth: I humbled my ſoul with faſting, and my prayer returned into mine own boſome, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter</hi> was kept in priſon, but earneſt prayer was made of the Church
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:35549:42"/>for him, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.5.</p>
               <p>Pray for the peace of Jeruſalem: they ſhall proſper that love thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.6.</p>
               <div type="litany">
                  <head>THE LETANY of Interceſsion.</head>
                  <p>THat it may pleaſe thee to bleſs thy Church militant here on earth, to preſerve the purity of doctrine, the due adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and the preaching of thy Word, that the gates of hell may not prevaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:35549:42"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to purge it from ſchiſm and hereſie, and to reconcile all unhappy differences, that we may keep the unity of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the bond of peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to fence it about with the wall of thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, to infatuate the counſel, &amp; to diſperſe the powers and projects of all thoſe that wiſh evill unto Sion.</p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:35549:43"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to hear me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to bleſſe that part of thy Church wherein thou haſt planted me, and to whoſe breſts thou haſt applied me, with peace and plenty, with a free exerciſe, and reverent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of all thine ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to hear me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to bleſs our gracious King <hi>Charls,</hi> our royall Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> our hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:35549:43"/>Prince <hi>Charls,</hi> and all others that are derived from that ſame ſacred ſtock, or ingraffed into it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to hear me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to bleſs the government &amp; preaching of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, make them painful in their Miniſtry, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary in their lives, that they may ſave themſelves and thoſe that hear them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:35549:44"/>to bleſſe the Councell with wiſedome, the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with integrity, the Magiſtrates with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, the people with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, &amp; our Armies with ſtrength &amp; victory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to bleſſe all ſchools and ſeminaries of learning &amp; religion; eſpecially the two Univerſities of this Land.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to he are me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:35549:44"/>to bleſſe all thoſe that are near and dear unto me by the bond of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or Chriſtian ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to bleſſe all thoſe that have been inſtruments of my good, and are yet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving: Such as have edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and inſtructed me: Such as have counſelled and adviſed me: Such as have clothed and fed me: ſuch as have reproved and corrected me when I ſinned.</p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:35549:45"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to hear me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to remember the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches beyond the ſeas, to repair the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines &amp; deſolations which her enemies have made in her, to reduce ſuch as are baniſhed, to inlarge ſuch as are impriſoned, to relieve ſuch as are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhed, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſuch as are perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the teſtimony of a good conſcience, and the truth of thy Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to hear me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:35549:45"/>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to raiſe up ſuch as are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected with the guilt of their own conſciences, with the horror of their fins, with the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thy wrath, with the weakneſſe of their graces, or jealouſies of thy mercy, and to ſay to their ſouls, that thou art their ſalvation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to proſper and aſsiſt all thoſe that jeopard their lives for the maintenance
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:35549:46"/>of the Goſpel, go forth with their Armies, cover their heads in the day of battel, and bring them home with honour and victory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to hear me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to bleſs all women with child with ſafe delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, all young children with a godly and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous education, the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with a proſperous voiage, the Husbandman with a plentifull harveſt, the captive with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:35549:46"/>and deliverance, and all priſoners with repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and amendment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to inſtruct the ignorant, to convert the obſtinate, to confirm the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to comfort the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, to binde up the broken-hearted, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie thoſe that erre, and to reduce them that wander, into the right way.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:35549:47"/>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to remember thine anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent people the Jewes, to open their eyes that they may ſee him whom they have pierced, and beleeve in him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to hear me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee in thy good time to bring in the fulneſſe of the Gentiles, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal the glorious light of thy Goſpel to ſuch as yet ſit in darkneſs and in the ſhadow of death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to hear me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:35549:47"/>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to forgive thoſe that perſecute and ſpeak evil of me, thoſe that injure and moleſt me, thoſe that ſlander and traduce me, and to ſoften the hearts of all thoſe that are mine enemies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O Lord hear my prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for my ſelf: O Lord hear my prayers for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: O Lord hear the prayers of thy Son Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt for us all, who ſits at thy right hand
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:35549:48"/>making interceſsion for us, and hath taught me to come to thee in this moſt perfect and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute form of prayer:</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <p>OUR Father which art in heaven, &amp;c.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <head>Morning Prayer.</head>
                        <p>O Lord our heavenly Father, almighty &amp; everlaſting God, which haſt ſafely brought us to the beginning of this day, defend us in the ſame with thy mighty power, &amp; grant that this day we fall into no ſin, neither run into any kind
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:35549:48"/>of danger, but that all our doings may be orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by thy governance, to doe alwayes that is righteous in thy ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <head>Evening Prayer.</head>
                        <p>LIghten our darkneſs, we beſeech thee, O Lord, and by thy great mercy defend us from all perils and dangers of this night, for the love of thy only Son our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="90" facs="tcp:35549:49"/>
                        <p>THE grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the love of God, &amp; the fellowſhip of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt be with us all evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A peculiar Letany to be uſed by, or for ſick perſons; Collected out of ſeverall places and paſſages of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture.</head>
               <p>IN thoſe dayes was <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſick unto death.</p>
               <p>Then turned he his face unto the wall, and prayed unto the Lord.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:35549:49"/>
               <p>And <hi>Hezekiah</hi> wept ſore. And the Lord ſaid, Behold, I will adde unto thy dayes fifteen years, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 38.1, 2, 3.</p>
               <div type="litany">
                  <head>THE LETANY.</head>
                  <p>O God the Father of heaven, whoſe property it is to kill and to make alive, to wound and to heal, to bring down to the grave, and to raiſe up again,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Have mercy upon me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thou who didſt heal
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:35549:50"/>
                     <hi>Naaman</hi> of his leproſie, <hi>David</hi> of his noiſome diſeaſe, <hi>Job</hi> of his ulcers, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> of his deſperate ſickneſſe,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Have mercy upon me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O Chriſt the Son of God, who madeſt the blinde to ſee, the dumb to ſpeak, the deaf to hear, and the lame to walk,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Have mercy upon me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thou who didſt cure <hi>Peters</hi> wives mother of her fever, the Centuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſervant of his palſie, the ten Lepers of their
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:35549:50"/>leproſie, and didſt help ſuch as were poſſeſſed with Divels,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Have mercy upon me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thou who didſt cure her that was diſeaſed with an iſſue of bloud twelve years, &amp; her that was bowed together eighteen years, and him at the pool of Betheſda that had an infirmity thirty and eight years,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Have mercy upon me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thou who didſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore to life the daughter of <hi>Jairus,</hi> &amp; the widows ſon, and raiſed up <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:35549:51"/>out of his grave,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Have mercy upon me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thou who didſt bear our ſickneſſes and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, thou who haſt ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thy ſelf the Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an of the ſick, thou who haſt called all ſuch as are weary and heavy laden to come unto thee, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing them eaſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Have mercy upon me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By thy faſting and watching, by thine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger &amp; thirſt, by thy grief and ſadneſs, by thy ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and bloudy ſweat, by
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:35549:51"/>thy cries and tears, by thy Croſſe and Paſſion,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Have mercy upon me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee, who diddeſt cure many diſeaſes by <hi>Peters</hi> ſhadow, many ſickneſſes by <hi>Pauls</hi> handkerchief, the eyes of the blind with clay &amp; ſpittle, the lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Naaman</hi> with the water of Jordan, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedſt up the dead by the bones of thy Prophet; to bleſſe all thoſe means that are or ſhall be uſed for my recovery.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to hear
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:35549:52"/>me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to give me grace to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my ſelf wholly to thy will; to take thy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation with patience &amp; thankfulneſs, &amp; to drink of this bitter cup with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out murmuring or repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to ſtreng then me againſt all the temptations of the divel, to ſuccour me in all the agonies &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts of mine own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:35549:52"/>and to lay no more upon me then thou ſhalt inable me to bear.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to hear me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee to continue unto me my memory and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, my ſpeech and ſenſes, the comforts and graces of thy holy Spirit, that I fall not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee, if it be thy will, to give me a longer time of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:35549:53"/>repentance, to reſcue me from the gates of the grave, to ſpare me a little before I go hence, and be no more ſeen, that I may ſtill praiſe thee in the land of the living.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech the to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it may pleaſe thee, if thou haſt appointed me for death, to fit and prepare me for it; to ſtrengthen my faith, to pardon and forgive me all my ſins, and to aſſure me of my ſalvation, that I may render up my ſoul
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:35549:53"/>with comfort and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to hear me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finally, that it may pleaſe thee when I have rendred it up, to receive it into thy hands, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me from the pangs of everlaſting death, and to ſet open unto me the gates of everlaſting life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech thee to heare me good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.2, 4, 5.</p>
                  <p>Have mercy upon me O Lord, for I am weak: O Lord heal me, for my
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:35549:54"/>bones are vexed.</p>
                  <p>Return O Lord, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my ſoul, O ſave me for thy mercies ſake.</p>
                  <p>For in death there is no remembrance of thee: and who ſhall give thee thanks in the pit?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.</p>
                  <p>Thine arrows ſtick faſt in me: and thy hand preſſeth me ſore, <hi>ver.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>There is no ſoundneſs in my fleſh, becauſe of thine anger; neither is there any reſt in my bones, becauſe of my ſin, <hi>ver.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:35549:54"/>
                  <p>For mine iniquities are gone over my head, as an heavy burded they are too heavy for me: <hi>ver.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>My wounds ſtink, and are corrupt, becauſe of my fooliſhneſs, <hi>ver.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>I am troubled, I am bowed down greatly: I go mourning all the day long, <hi>ver.</hi> 6.</p>
                  <p>My loins are filled with a loathſome diſeaſe, and there is no ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in my fleſh, <hi>ver.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>I am feeble and ſore broken, I have rored by reaſon of the diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:35549:55"/>of my heart, <hi>ver.</hi> 8.</p>
                  <p>Lord, all my deſire is before thee, &amp; my groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is not hid from thee, <hi>ver.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p>Forſake me not O Lord, O my God be not far from me, <hi>ver.</hi> 21.</p>
                  <p>Make haſte to help me, O Lord my ſalvation, <hi>ver.</hi> 22.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="directions_and_prayers">
               <head>DIRECTIONS for the Lords Day.</head>
               <p>HEE that would ſpend a Sunday well, (living where he hath the liberty
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:35549:55"/>of Gods houſe and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances) muſt do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before Church, ſomething at Church, ſomething after Church.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Before Church.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. So ſoone as we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, we ſhould have our hearts affected with the majeſty and ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the day, putting a difference betwixt it and others, conſidering that it is
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Lords day.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An holy day.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>An honourable day.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Great is the <hi>honour</hi> of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:35549:56"/>this day above others.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God the Father honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>On this day he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the elements of the world.</p>
                  <p>On this day he crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Angels.</p>
                  <p>On this day he firſt rained Manna upon the Iſraelites.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God the Son honoured it</hi> with his glorious reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, with his gracious apparitions after he was riſen. For</p>
                  <p>On this day he appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the two <hi>Maries</hi>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:35549:56"/>that came to the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.1, 9.</p>
                  <p>On this day he appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his Diſciples aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled together, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> then not being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>John</hi> 20.19.</p>
                  <p>On this day he appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red again to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>Thomas</hi> being with them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.26.</p>
                  <p>On this day S. <hi>John</hi> ſaw him walking in the midſt of the ſeven gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Candleſticks, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.10, 13.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God the holy Ghoſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:35549:57"/>
                  <p>On this day he deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the Apoſtles in a golden ſhowr of all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall gifts and graces. Since which time, <hi>The Church hath honoured it,</hi> and made it the day of their ſolemn Aſſemblies, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7.</p>
                  <p>What God and his Church hath thus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, that do not thou profane.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> we muſt lay aſide the cares of the world, and the works of our ordinary callings, leaving them behind us,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:35549:57"/>as <hi>Abraham</hi> did his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants when he went to offer his ſacrifice upon Mount <hi>Moriah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> we muſt cleanſe our ſelves by <hi>confeſsion</hi> &amp; repentance, for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe our prayers in the Church will not be <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable</hi> to God, nor his ordinances <hi>profitable</hi> to us.</p>
                  <p>Will ye ſteal, murder, &amp; commit adultery, and ſwear falſly, and burn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe unto Baal, and walk after other gods, whom ye know not, and come
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:35549:58"/>and ſtand before me in this houſe? <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.9, 10.</p>
                  <p>Shall I be enquired of by <hi>you,</hi> ô houſe of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> As I live, ſaith the Lord, I will not be enquired of by <hi>you, Ezek.</hi> 20.31.</p>
                  <p>God heareth not <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners:</hi> but if any man be a worſhipper of him, and doth his will, him he heareth, <hi>John</hi> 9.31.</p>
                  <p>The Lord had reſpect unto <hi>Abel,</hi> and his offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: But unto <hi>Cain</hi> and his offering he had not reſpect, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.4, 5.</p>
                  <p>I will waſh my hands
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:35549:58"/>in innocency, and <hi>ſo</hi> will I compaſſe thine Altar, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.6.</p>
                  <p>Hence was it that the Jews writ over the doors of their Synagogues this ſaying of <hi>David,</hi> This is the gate of the Lord, the <hi>righteous</hi> ſhall enter into it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.20.</p>
                  <p>And now being thus qualified &amp; prepared, go unto the houſe of God, and in the way meditate of ſome of theſe ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:</p>
                  <p>One thing I have deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Lord that I
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:35549:59"/>will ſeek after: that I may dwel in the houſe of the Lord all the days of my life, to behold the beauty of the Lord, and to enquire in his Temple <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4.</p>
                  <p>I was glad when they ſaid unto me, Let us go up unto the houſe of the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.1.</p>
                  <p>We will go unto his Tabernacles, we wil wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip at his footſtoole, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.7.</p>
                  <p>My ſoul longeth, yea even fainteth for the courts of the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:35549:59"/>
                  <head>A ſhort morning Prayer for the Sunday.</head>
                  <p>O Moſt glorious, and immortall God, the eye of whoſe providence doth never ſlumber, I yeeld thee humble and hearty thanks that thou haſt preſerved me from the perils of the night paſt, &amp; brought me ſafe to the light of this day, and the comforts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. It is a day holy and honourable, a day which is conſecrated to thine own ſervice, and ſet apart
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:35549:60"/>for thine own honour: Let my heart therefore, gracious God, be ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the glory and majeſty of it, that I may not doe mine own works, nor ſeek mine own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, nor ſpeak mine own words; but may wait upon thee in the uſe of thine ordinances, &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thoſe weighty duties which thou requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of me.</p>
                  <p>Now foraſmuch as thou art a God of pure eyes, and wilt be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in all thoſe that draw
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:35549:60"/>near unto thee, a God who regardeſt not the ſacrifice of fools, nor heareſt ſinners though they tread in thy courts, and call upon thee in the Houſe of praier; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee to pard on and forgive me all my ſins, remove them out of thy preſence, as far as the Eaſt is from the Weſt: accept of me in the death and paſſion of thy Son Jeſus Chriſt, that when I ſhall come into thy Temple, to compaſſe thine Altar, my prayer
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:35549:61"/>may come up before thee as incenſe, and the lifting up of my hands as the evening ſacrifice. And as I deſire that thou wouldeſt hear me calling upon thee in my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſo give me grace to hear thee calling upon me in thy word. It is the word of truth, of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, of righteouſneſſe, of reconciliation, &amp; that Word which is able to ſave my ſoul in the day of the Lord Jeſus; grant therefore that I may hear it with reverence, receive
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:35549:61"/>it with meekneſſe, and mingle it with faith, that it may accompliſh in me that good work for which thou haſt ſent it.</p>
                  <p>And that this day may be every where a day of holineſſe unto thee; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie, and prepare the hearts of all thy people for thy ſervice, fill the places of thy worſhip with thy glory, be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the aſſemblies of thy Saints, open the mouths of thy Miniſters, &amp; ſecond the miniſtry of thy word by the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:35549:62"/>of thy Spirit, that it may be powerfull to the caſting down of the ſtrong holds of ſin, and Satan, to the advancing &amp; inlarging of thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to the edifying &amp; building up of thy body the Church, and to the perfecting of thy Saints, till we all come to the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, to a perfect man: Thou ô God who art able to do exceeding abundantly for us, above all that we can ask or
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:35549:62"/>think, hear me, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer me, even for the ſake of thy dear Sonne Jeſus Chriſt: to whom, with the Father, and the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit, be aſcribed &amp; given all power, praiſe, might, majeſty and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion now and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>At Church.</head>
                  <p>COnſider firſt the place where thou art; it is
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The gate of heaven</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Holy ground</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The houſe of God</hi>
                        </l>
                        <bibl>Joſh. 5.15. Gen. 28.17.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:35549:63"/>
                  <p>O how amiable are thy tabernacles, ô Lord of Hoſts! A day in thy Courts is better then a thouſand. Bleſſed are they that may dwell in thy houſe, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 84.1, 4, 10.</p>
                  <p>Then be carefull to diſcharge thoſe duties which God there requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of thee, and they ordinarily are two;
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Prayer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Hearing the Word.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>In prayer, <hi>firſt look to the devotion of thy ſoul.</hi> It muſt be the lifting up of the ſoul, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.1.</p>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:35549:63"/>
                  <p>The powring out of the ſoul, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.15.</p>
                  <p>A ſtrong crying, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7.</p>
                  <p>A wraſtling with God. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.4.</p>
                  <p>Without this thy prayer will be but bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.7.</p>
                  <p>The howling of a dog, or wolf, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.14.</p>
                  <p>A bell without a clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
                  <p>A pile of wood with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fire.</p>
                  <p>A bullet without pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
                  <p>A bird without wings.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:35549:64"/>A cloud without water. A tinkling cymball.</p>
                  <p>The Jews writ this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence alſo over the doors of their Synagogues, and Oratories, <hi>Prayer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intention, is as the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy without the ſoul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then in the next place, <hi>look to the reverence of thy body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God is greatly to be feared in the aſſembly of the Saints: and to be had in reverence of all them that are about him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.7.</p>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:35549:64"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Uncover thy head.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The four and twenty Elders fell down before him that ſate on the throne, caſting their <hi>crowns</hi> from their heads. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bend thy knee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O come let us wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and bow down: let us <hi>kneel</hi> before the Lord our Maker. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.6.</p>
                  <p>The other duty is the <hi>hearing</hi> of the <hi>word</hi> read and preached, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of us,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt, attention.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Speak Lord, for thy
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:35549:65"/>ſervant <hi>heareth,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.10.</p>
                  <p>Hearken O daughter and conſider, and incline thine <hi>eare, Pſal.</hi> 45.10.</p>
                  <p>I will <hi>hear</hi> what God the Lord will ſpeak unto me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.8.</p>
                  <p>The Lord opened the heart of <hi>Lydia,</hi> that ſhe <hi>attended</hi> unto the things that were ſpoken by <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 16.14.</p>
                  <p>He that hath an eare let him <hi>heare</hi> what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.11. My ſheep <hi>hear</hi> my voice, <hi>John</hi> 10.27.</p>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:35549:65"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And for this end we muſt conſider it is</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>The word of <hi>God,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13.</item>
                        <item>The word of <hi>Grace, Act.</hi> 14.3.</item>
                        <item>The word of <hi>truth, John</hi> 17.17.</item>
                        <item>The word of <hi>reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19.</item>
                        <item>The word of <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Heb.</hi> 5.13.</item>
                        <item>The word of <hi>faih, Rom.</hi> 10.8.</item>
                        <item>The word of <hi>etenal life, John</hi> 9.68.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That it is</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>Good <hi>ſeed, Mark</hi> 4.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:35549:66"/>
                  <p>Sincere <hi>milk,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. Strong <hi>meat, Heb.</hi> 5.14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That it is</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A wholſom word, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3.</p>
                  <p>A lively word, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</p>
                  <p>A good word, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That it is</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Better then thouſands of gold and ſilver. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.72.</p>
                  <p>Sweeter then the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and the hony comb. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.10.</p>
                  <p>And all this, becauſe it is that word which is able to ſave our ſouls. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.21.</p>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:35549:66"/>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>the hearing of the Word requires retenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as well as attention.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore ye ſhall <hi>lay up</hi> theſe my words in your heart, and in your ſoul, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.18.</p>
                  <p>Thy word have <hi>I hid</hi> in mine heart, that I might not ſin againſt thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mary kept</hi> all theſe ſayings in her heart. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.51.</p>
                  <p>And laſtly, <hi>people muſt be here admoniſhed not to depart from the Church till the Miniſter hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35549:67"/>the bleſsing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>All the people depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted every man to his houſe, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.42.</p>
                  <p>But it was after <hi>David</hi> had made an end of offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the burnt offerings and the peace offerings, and had <hi>bleſſed</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the name of the Lord, <hi>ver.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>Surely there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the <hi>bleſsing</hi> of the Miniſter. Then the Prieſts and the Levites aroſe, and <hi>bleſſed</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and their voice was <hi>heard,</hi> and their prayer
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:35549:67"/>
                     <hi>came up</hi> to his holy dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place, even unto heaven, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.37.</p>
                  <p>Leave not then thine Angel, till he hath given thee a bleſsing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>AFTER CHURCH.</head>
                  <p>AND now being come home, it is thy duty yet further,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>To meditate upon ſuch things as have been taught thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>His delight is in the Law of the Lord, and in that Law doth he <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate</hi> day and night, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.2.</p>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:35549:68"/>
                  <p>O how I love thy Law! it is my <hi>meditation</hi> all the day, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.97.</p>
                  <p>I have more under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding then all my tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers: for thy Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are my <hi>Meditation, verſ.</hi> 99.</p>
                  <p>My <hi>meditation</hi> of him ſhal be ſweet, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104.34.</p>
                  <p>My heart was hot within me, while I was <hi>muſing,</hi> the fire burned. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.3.</p>
                  <p>The beaſts that chew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not the cud were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>thou muſt
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:35549:68"/>praiſe God for ſo much of the means as he was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to afford thee that day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Bleſſed be the God &amp; Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who hath bleſſed us with all ſpiritual bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in heavenly things, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.3.</p>
                  <p>As the liberty of his <hi>houſe;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The comfort of his <hi>Day;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The communion of his <hi>Saints;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The inſtruction of his <hi>Word;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The diſpenſation of his <hi>Sacraments;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:35549:69"/>
                  <p>The gifts of his <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>we muſt pray for a bleſsing upon the means of our ſalvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He only it is that can put his Law in our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts and write it in our hearts, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> may plant, and <hi>Apollos</hi> water; but God gives the increaſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</p>
                  <p>The excellency of the power is of God, &amp; not of us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, <hi>teach it thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:35549:69"/>
                  <p>You ſhall <hi>teach</hi> them your children, talking of them when thou fitteſt in thine houſe, and when thou walkeſt by the way, when thou lieſt down, and when thou riſeſt up, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.19.</p>
                  <p>I know him, that hee will command his <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> and his <hi>houſhold</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, to keep the way of the Lord, to doe ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and judgment, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.16.</p>
                  <p>I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.15.</p>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:35549:70"/>
                  <p>If thou doeſt thus ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie this Day of reſt here, thou ſhalt celebrate an everlaſting reſt and Sabbath hereafter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All manner of perſons within the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ſhall from henceforth celebrate &amp; keep the Lords day, commonly called Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and other holy days, according to Gods holy wil and pleaſure, and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land preſcribed in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half; that is, in hearing the word of God read and taught, in private and
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:35549:70"/>publick prayers, in acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging their offences to God, and amendment of the ſame; in reconciling themſelves charitably to their neighbours, where diſpleaſure hath been; in oftentimes receiving the communion of the body &amp; bloud of Chriſt; in viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the poore and ſick, uſing all good and ſober converſation.</hi> Canon 13. of thoſe 1603.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:35549:71"/>
                  <head>A ſhort Evening Prayer for the Lords day.</head>
                  <p>O Moſt glorious God, and in Jeſus Chriſt my mercifull and loving Father: I confeſſe, and acknowledge thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny weakneſſes &amp; imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections which have paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from me in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the duties of this day. I have called upon thee for the pardon and forgiveneſſe of my ſins, but ſo coldly and careleſſy, that my very
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:35549:71"/>prayers are become ſins, and ſtand in need of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</p>
                  <p>I have heard thy holy Word, but with ſuch deadneſſe, &amp; diſtraction of ſpirit, that I have been a very unprofitable and forgetfull hearer. So that O Lord, though I have done thy work, yet I have done it ſo negligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that I may rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a curſe then a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from thee.</p>
                  <p>But O God, who art rich in mercy and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in redemption;
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:35549:72"/>mark not what amiſſe hath paſſed from me, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that I am but duſt; pardon, and paſſe by all my ſins, negligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and ignorances, look not upon the weakneſſe of my fleſh, but upon the willingneſs of my ſpirit, and ſo cover all my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and abſolute obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of thy dear Son, that thoſe Sacrifices which I have offered up unto thee this day, may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, in, and for that ſacrifice which Chriſt
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:35549:72"/>Jeſus offered up upon the croſs for me.</p>
                  <p>And as I deſire that my ſacrifices may be pleaſing to thee, ſo let thine ordinances be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to me. And as thou haſt this day ſown my heart with the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſeed of thy Word, ſo let neither the fowls of the air devour it, nor the cares of the world choak it, but let the gracious rain of thy bleſſing come often upon it, that it may bring forth in mee the fruits of repentance and
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:35549:73"/>amendment of life.</p>
                  <p>And foraſmuch as thy Word is an unvaluable &amp; ineſtimable treaſure, better then thouſands of gold and ſilver, ſweeter alſo then the hony &amp; the hony comb; bleſſed Lord God be pleaſed ſtill to continue it to our Land and Nation, let not our crying ſins of unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, impenitency, hardneſs of heart, &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfulneſſe under ſo great means of grace, cauſe thee to remove thy candleſtick, or to quench
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:35549:73"/>the light of our Iſrael. Inlighten alſo with the beams of thy Goſpel thoſe nations which yet ſit in darkneſs and in the ſhadow of death: adde unto thy Church daily ſuch as ſhal be ſaved, that ſo theſe ſinful days being ſhortned, &amp; the number of thine elect accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, we may celebrate that eternal reſt and Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath of our ſouls with thee in thy Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſe O Lord all the people of this land, from the higheſt to the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt;
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:35549:74"/>our King &amp; Queen, our Prince, &amp; the reſt of the roiall ſtock; our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Magiſtrates, thy whole Church, and every member of it, in what place or caſe ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: and proſper all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and enterpriſes that are undertaken for the advancement of the Goſpel, and the inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>Finally, O Lord, as thou haſt been good to me in the paſſages of this day, refreſhing my body with thy good creatures,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:35549:74"/>and my ſoul with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall reſt of this holy Day: ſo continue thy goodneſs to mee this night, receive me into the arms of thy providence, cover me with the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of thy wings, that I may lay me down in peace, and take my reſt, that being awakened to the comforts of the next day, my mouth may be filled with thy praiſes; and I may doe thee ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in the duties of that calling wherein thou haſt placed &amp; diſpoſed of me:
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:35549:75"/>that ſo thy good bleſsing may be ſtill upon me; and thou maiſt never be weary to doe me good: all this, and what elſe thou knoweſt needfull and expedient for me, I beg in the name, merits, mediation, and words of thy Sonne Chriſt Jeſus, ſaying as he himſelf hath taught me:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Our Father, which art in heaven, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:35549:75"/>
               <head>Directions for the due receiving of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WEE may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to come to the Lords Table without a due &amp; ſerious preparation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which is holy muſt not bee given to Dogges: neither muſt pearls bee caſt before ſwine, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joſiah</hi> charged the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites to prepare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to pray for their brethren, and ſo to
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:35549:76"/>kill the paſſeover, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 35.4, 6.</p>
               <p>The neglect of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is very dangerous.</p>
               <p>After the ſop Satan enters into <hi>Judas, John</hi> 13.27.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall eat this bread, and drink this cup of the Lord <hi>unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily,</hi> ſhal be guilty of the body and bloud of the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27.</p>
               <p>Hee that eateth and drinketh <hi>unworthily,</hi> ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and drinketh dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation unto himſelf, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29.</p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:35549:76"/>
               <p>For <hi>this cauſe</hi> many are weak, and ſickly among you, and many ſleep, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now this preparation conſiſts principally in five things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt is a <hi>ſelf-exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let a man <hi>examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> and ſo let him eate of that bread, and drink of that cup.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28.</p>
               <p>The thing chiefly to be examined, is <hi>ſin:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In <hi>thought:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The thoughts of our
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:35549:77"/>hearts are only <hi>evil,</hi> and that continually, <hi>Gen</hi> 6.5</p>
               <p>Out of the heart pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed evill <hi>thoughts, Mat.</hi> 15.19.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In <hi>word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idle words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay unto you, that of every <hi>idle word</hi> that men ſhall ſpeak, they ſhall give account thereof at the day of judgement, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.36.</p>
               <p>Filthy and <hi>immodeſt words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let no <hi>corrupt</hi> commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication proceed out of your mouth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.22.</p>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:35549:77"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Angry</hi> and <hi>raſh words;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As calling our borther <hi>Raca,</hi> or <hi>Thou fool, Mat.</hi> 5.29.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Falſe</hi> and <hi>untrue words,</hi> as lies, ſlanders, defama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever loveth, or maketh a <hi>lie,</hi> is ſhut out of the new <hi>Jeruſalem, Rev.</hi> 22.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Profane and impious words.</hi> Againſt GOD oathes and blaſphemies.</p>
               <p>Let your communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be yea, yea; nay nay; for whatſoever is more then theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:35549:78"/>of evil, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.37.</p>
               <p>Againſt <hi>our ſelves</hi> or <hi>others,</hi> as curſes, impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>As he loved curſing, ſo let it come unto him.</p>
               <p>As he clothed himſelf with curſing, like as with a garment: ſo let it come into his bowels like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and like oyle into his bones, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.18.19.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>In deed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is either of</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Omiſsion,</hi> or</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Commiſsion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Both are pointed at in that ſentence of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle:</p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:35549:78"/>
               <p>The good which I would do, I doe not:</p>
               <p>But the evill which I would not do, that I do, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.19.</p>
               <p>Thus you have the thing to be examined.</p>
               <p>Now the rule of this <hi>examination</hi> muſt be the <hi>Law</hi> of God.</p>
               <p>For by the <hi>Law</hi> is the knowledg of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20.</p>
               <p>I had not known <hi>ſin,</hi> but by the <hi>Law, Rom.</hi> 7.7.</p>
               <p>Hence it is that our Church (which hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed all things wiſely,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:35549:79"/>and ſweetly in the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy) hath appointed the commandments to be read before the admim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that men might ſee their ſins in the glaſſe of Gods <hi>Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of a worthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is <hi>Repentance and Contrition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Paſchall Lambe was to be eaten with <hi>ſowr herbs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Chriſt our Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over muſt be received with a <hi>broken</hi> and a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite</hi> ſpirit.</p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:35549:79"/>
               <p>With a bitter ſoul.</p>
               <p>With a weeping eye.</p>
               <p>This bread muſt be eaten with the ſweat of our brows, <hi>i.e.</hi> our tears.</p>
               <p>And I may ſay of the wine in this Sacrament, as the Mother of <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid unto him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.6.</p>
               <p>Give this wine unto ſuch as bee of <hi>heavy</hi> hearts. And though in the ſenſe of our own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe we may cry out with <hi>Paul,</hi> Who is fit for theſe things?</p>
               <p>Yet we may comfort our ſelves with that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt;</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:35549:80"/>
               <p>A broken and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heart O God thou wilt not deſpiſe, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The third thing requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of a Comunicant, is</hi> Faith.</p>
               <p>He muſt <hi>beleeve,</hi> that Jeſus Chriſt is the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias, and Saviour of the world.</p>
               <p>He muſt <hi>beleeve,</hi> that he was crucified, &amp; ſhed his bloud.</p>
               <p>He muſt <hi>beleeve,</hi> that the merits of his croſſe and paſsion are able to ſave ſinners.</p>
               <p>He muſt <hi>beleeve;</hi> that
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:35549:80"/>theſe merits are convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>him</hi> in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being <hi>rightly admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred,</hi> and <hi>duly received:</hi> For what was bequeath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Teſtament,</hi> is diſpenſed in the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>faith</hi> is the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding garment: he that intruded to the feaſt without it, was bound hand &amp; foot, and caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to utter darkneſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly, there is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a ſtedfaſt purpoſe and ſettled reſolution againſt ſin for the trme to come.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:35549:81"/>
               <p>The Church in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament cals ſuch only, <hi>as intend to lead a new life, to follow the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God, to walk from thenceforth in his holy ways.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Paſchall Lambe was to be eaten by ſuch only as were <hi>circumciſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Manna</hi> was to be put into a pot of <hi>pure</hi> gold. The body of <hi>Chriſt</hi> crucified was wrapt in <hi>fine</hi> linnen, and laid in a <hi>new</hi> Spulchre.</p>
               <p>Sorrow for ſin without
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:35549:81"/>reſolution of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is like the pumping in a Ship without ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the leak that lets in the water.</p>
               <p>In the Law, if a man held the unclean thing ſtill in his hand, he was unclean, though he waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his hand never ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, there is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Charity with all men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Paſchall Lambe was to be eaten without <hi>leaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Serpent diſgorges his poiſon, when he coms
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:35549:82"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:35549:82"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:35549:83"/>to drink: Be as wiſe as Serpents.</p>
               <p>Let us keep the feaſt, not with old leaven, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the leaven of <hi>malice,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8.</p>
               <p>If thou bring thy gift to the Altar, and there remembreſt that thy brother hath ought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee:</p>
               <p>Leave there thy gift before the altar, and go thy way, firſt be <hi>reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.23, 24.</p>
               <p>The three wiſe men
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:35549:83"/>went firſt to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> &amp; then to <hi>Bethlehem;</hi> firſt to the viſion of peace, then to the houſe of <hi>bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The cup of bleſſing which we bleſſe, is it not the <hi>Communion</hi> of the bloud of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>The bread which we break, is it not the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> of the body of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>For we being many, are <hi>one</hi> bread, and <hi>one</hi> body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16, 17.</p>
               <p>The ſigns of bread &amp; wine uſed in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may teach us <hi>love</hi> &amp; <hi>charity.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:35549:84"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Many</hi> grains are kneaded together into <hi>one</hi> loafe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Many</hi> grapes are preſſed together in <hi>one</hi> cup.</p>
               <p>If thus thou haſt made thy peace with God, and the world, draw neare, <hi>Taſt and ſee how ſweet the Lord is,</hi> Pſal. 34.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eate O friend, drink, yea drink abundantly, O beloved,</hi> Cant. 5.1.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A ſhort Prayer before we receive the Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>O Moſt gracious and merciful Lord God, thou haſt called all thoſe
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:35549:84"/>that are weary &amp; heavy laden with the burthen of their ſins to come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, and haſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that thou wilt eaſe and refreſh them; thou haſt invited all thoſe that hunger and thirſt after thy Kingdome, and the righteouſneſſe thereof, to come to thy Table, to taſte of thy Supper, and haſt promiſed that thou wilt ſatisfie them.</p>
                  <p>In affiance therefore of theſe promiſes, I come to thee bleſſed Lord Jeſus, beſeeching thee to eaſe
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:35549:85"/>me to refreſh me, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie me with thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, for my ſoul hungers and thirſts after thee, &amp; thy ſalvation.</p>
                  <p>I confeſſe and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that my daily ſins have made me unworthy of my daily bread; much more of this Manna, this bread of life, which came down from heaven.</p>
                  <p>I confeſſe alſo that I am not prepared accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the preparation of thy Sanctuary; yet for as much as I have this day ſet my heart to ſeek
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:35549:85"/>thee, thou O good God be merciful unto me.</p>
                  <p>And though I cannot bring with me a clean heart (for who can ſay his heart is clean?) yet behold O Lord, I bring with me a contrite heart and a broken ſpirit, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe not O God this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. As for the ſinnes that I have committed againſt thee, binde them up into one bundle, and caſt them into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe ſea of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, bury them in the wounds, and waſh them
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:35549:86"/>away in the bloud of that immaculate Lamb Chriſt Jeſus; and for the time to come ſo ſprinkle my conſcience with the ſame bloud, that being clenſed from dead works I may ſerve thee the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and true holineſs all the days of my life. That ſo this bleſſed Sacrament may be a means to quiet my conſcience, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe my faith, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame my charity, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my life, to ſave my ſoul, &amp; to aſſure me that
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:35549:86"/>I am in the number of thoſe bleſſed ones, who ſhal eate at thy table, and be called to the marriage ſupper of the Lamb.</p>
                  <p>Grant this O Lord for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, in whoſe name and words I conclude theſe my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect prayers, ſaying as he himſelf hath taught me, <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>At the receiving of this Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>IN the receiving of the Lords Supper many particulars would rather
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:35549:87"/>diſtract us, then direct us; theſe few I ſuppoſe moſt conſiderable.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, let thine <hi>eyes</hi> be upon the <hi>actions</hi> of the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> obſerve the <hi>breaking</hi> of the <hi>bread,</hi> and the powring out of the wine.</p>
                  <p>The breaking of the bread will minde thee how the body of Chriſt was bruiſed and broken.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>pouring out of the wine</hi> wil reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber thee of the <hi>ſhedding of his bloud.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was ſhed for thee:</p>
                  <p>When he was <hi>circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:35549:87"/>
                  <p>When he was <hi>ſcourged.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When he ſweat in the <hi>garden.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When he was <hi>crowned</hi> with <hi>thorns.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But eſpecially, to which this Sacrament hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate relation,</p>
                  <p>When he was <hi>nailed to the croſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When <hi>his fide was pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The bloud of Chriſt clenſeth us from all ſins, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.17.</p>
                  <p>It ſpeaketh better things then the bloud of <hi>Abel, Heb.</hi> 12.24.</p>
                  <pb n="166" facs="tcp:35549:88"/>
                  <p>It is precious bloud, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. And all this becauſe it is the bloud of <hi>God, Acts</hi> 20.28.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>diſcern</hi> the Lords body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29.</p>
                  <p>We muſt conſider the <hi>conſecrated bread,</hi> not as the bread of the Lord, but as that bread <hi>which is the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Not as our common, ordinary, &amp; daily bread, but as the <hi>body of Chriſt ſacramentally.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We muſt conſider the <hi>wine,</hi> not as the bloud of the <hi>grape,</hi> but as the <hi>bloud</hi>
                     <pb n="167" facs="tcp:35549:88"/>of Chriſt in a true, yet <hi>ſacramentall</hi> manner.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt is truly preſent in the Sacrament; it is the eating of his fleſh, and the drinking of his bloud, <hi>John</hi> 6.56.</p>
                  <p>Not naturally, and corporally.</p>
                  <p>This is an hard ſaying, who can hear it? <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.60.</p>
                  <p>The fleſh profiteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, the words that I ſpeak unto you, they are ſpirit, and life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.63.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, receive it <hi>kneeling.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:35549:89"/>
                  <p>This geſture is moſt ſutable.</p>
                  <p>It ſignifies an humble and gratefull acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits we receive in this Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>Again, the Miniſter when he gives, and we when we receive, joyn together in a ſhort, but ſweet prayer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt which was given for thee, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The bloud of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt which was ſhed for thee, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:35549:89"/>
                  <p>No geſture ſo ſutable for prayer as kneeling.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Again, it is appointed &amp; ordered by the Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let all things be done <hi>decently,</hi> and in order, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.</p>
                  <p>Though I be abſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you in the fleſh, yet am I preſent with you in the ſpirit, joying, and behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your <hi>order, Col.</hi> 2.5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>After the receiving of this Sacrament.</head>
                  <p>WHen thou haſt been partaker of the Lords Supper;</p>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:35549:90"/>
                  <p>Firſt of all <hi>give thanks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is a duty which we owe for our ordinary ſuppers.</p>
                  <p>It was called the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt,</hi> from this duty of <hi>thankſgiving.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is the cup of bleſſing.</p>
                  <p>God bleſſeth us, and we muſt bleſſe God.</p>
                  <p>God gives us the cup of <hi>ſalvation,</hi> and we muſt take the cup of <hi>thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Diſciples when they had received it, ſang an <hi>Hymne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And an <hi>Hymne</hi> is a
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:35549:90"/>ſong of praiſe and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 29.30.</p>
                  <p>Expreſs thy thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in Pſalmes, and Hymnes, and ſpirituall ſongs; <hi>publickly</hi> in the congregation, <hi>privately</hi> in thine own family.</p>
                  <p>Pſalmes fit for this, are <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, as there muſt be <hi>thankſgiving to God;</hi> ſo there muſt be <hi>almſgiving</hi> to the poor.</p>
                  <p>It was a cuſtome in the Primitive Church, and is ſtill continued in many
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:35549:91"/>places, to have gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and collections for the poor at the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Davids</hi> ſervants told <hi>Nabal</hi> that they came to him in a good day, for it was a day of feaſting, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.8.</p>
                  <p>This is a day of <hi>feaſting to thee;</hi> Let it not be a day <hi>of faſting</hi> to thy poor brethren.</p>
                  <p>God hath fed thee with the <hi>bread of life,</hi> &amp; canſt thou deny the crums of bread that fall from thy table?</p>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:35549:91"/>
                  <p>He hath refreſhed thee <hi>with the bloud of his Son,</hi> with the <hi>wine of his ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary,</hi> &amp; canſt thou deny the drink of thy buttery, or a cup of cold water?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Give chearfully.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God loves a chearfull giver, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Give liberally.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Conſider how great a gift God hath this day beſtowed upon thee:
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>His Son.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>His begotten Son.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>His only begotten Son.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>His beloved Son.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>His dear Son, Col.</hi> 1.13.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:35549:92"/>
                  <p>Thirdly, take heed thou <hi>relapſe</hi> not into thy <hi>old ſins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have waſhed my feet, how ſhall I defile them? <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.3.</p>
                  <p>If after we have eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the pollutions of the world, through the knowledge of our Lord &amp; Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, we be <hi>again</hi> intangled therein and overcome;</p>
                  <p>If with the Dog we return to our own vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit again: or with the Sow that was waſhed, to our wallowing in the mire;</p>
                  <pb n="175" facs="tcp:35549:92"/>
                  <p>The latter end will be worſe with us then the beginning, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20, 22</p>
                  <p>Of how much ſorer puniſhment, ſuppoſe ye, ſhall he be thought wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, who hath troden under foot the Sonne of God, and hath counted the bloud of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant wherewith he was ſanctified, an unholy thing, and hath done de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite unto the ſpirit of grace? <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29.</p>
                  <p>When the unclean ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is gone out of a man, he ſaith, I will return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:35549:93"/>my houſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence I came out, and when he is come he findeth it em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty, ſwept, &amp; garniſhed. Then goeth he, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth with him ſeven o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirits more wicked then himſelf, and they enter in, and dwell there. And the laſt eſtate of that man is worſe then the firſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.43, 44, 45.</p>
                  <p>He that waſheth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf after the touching of a dead body, if he touch it again, what availeth his waſhing? <hi>Ecclus</hi> 34.25.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="177" facs="tcp:35549:93"/>
                  <head>A ſhort prayer after the receiving of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
                  <p>O Moſt gracious God from whoſe bounty every good and perfect gift is derived, I, and all that is within me, praiſe and magnifie thy holy name for all the mercies and favours which from time to time thou haſt beſtowed upon me.</p>
                  <p>Eſpecially I thank thee for thy Son Jeſus Chriſt the fountain and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all bleſsings; that
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:35549:94"/>thou haſt ſent him into the world to take our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon him, and to die for us; and that thou haſt fed me who am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the leaſt of thy favours, with the precious merits of his death and paſſion. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord God, thou haſt been pleaſed this day to ſet thy ſeal to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and forgiveneſſe of all my ſins, oh let me not tear it off again by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe, or relap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing into my old ſinnes, from which thou haſt
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:35549:94"/>purged me, leſt my laſt end be worſe then my beginning. But when hereafter I ſhall be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted by the divel, allured by the world, or provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by mine own fleſh, lay before mine eyes by thy remembring Spirit how deare the expiation of my ſins coſt my Lord &amp; Saviour Chriſt Jeſus, even the effuſion of his moſt precious and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred bloud; that in the contemplation of his death, and application of his moſt bitter paſſion, I
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:35549:95"/>may die daily unto ſin, and ſo ſhew the Lords death till he come; That when he ſhall come, and bring his reward with him, I may receive that crown of righteouſneſſe which he hath purchaſed &amp; prepared for all thoſe that love and expect the day of his appearing, with the precious price of his incorruptible blood.</p>
                  <p>And whereas I have this day renewed my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with thee my God, in vows, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:35549:95"/>of better obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, aſſiſt me by thy grace, and ſtrengthen me by thy power, that I may pay the vows which I have made unto thee; &amp; that by virtue of thy heavenly nouriſhment, I may grow up in grace &amp; godlineſs, till at laſt I come to be a perfect man in Chriſt Jeſus, in whoſe moſt bleſſed name and words, I conclude theſe my imperfect prayers, ſaying as he himſelf hath taught me:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:35549:96"/>
               <head>EVERY DAYES Conſiderations.</head>
               <p>Conſider
<list>
                     <item>1. What good thou haſt done</item>
                     <item>2. What good thou daily doeſt.</item>
                     <item>3. What thou ſhalt do hereafter.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider theſe in
<list>
                     <item>The Morning when thou riſeſt.</item>
                     <item>The Day when thou walkeſt.</item>
                     <item>The Night when thou wakeſt.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Conſiderations wel meditated on, will the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prepare thee for theſe enſuing meditations of Death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:35549:96"/>
               <head>SECTION I. <hi>Meditations of Death.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE life of a Chriſtian is or ſhould be a continuall meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of death.</p>
               <p>The flight of a Bird is directed by her train, the courſe of a ſhip is ſteered by the helm, ſo is the
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:35549:97"/>life of a man ordered by the ſerious appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of his laſt end.</p>
               <p>The firſt man was called <hi>Adam,</hi> which ſignifies a piece of red earth.</p>
               <p>He was cloathed in the skins of dead beaſts.</p>
               <p>He was adjudged to the earth, to dig, and delve in it. God
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:35549:97"/>would have his name, his garments, his imploiment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of his grave, and monitors of his mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality. It is reported by the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that the people of God uſed the 90. <hi>Pſalm</hi> in form of a daily prayer.</p>
               <p>In which Pſalm there is a long ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:35549:98"/>of the ſhortneſſe of our lives: and this petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to God:</p>
               <p>So teach us to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our days, that we may apply our hearts to wiſdome, <hi>ver.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>Oh that they were wiſe, that they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood this, that they would conſider their later end. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.29.</p>
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:35549:98"/>
               <p>Whatſoever thou takeſt in hand, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the end, &amp; thou ſhalt never do amiſſe, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.36.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. I. <hi>That the meditation of death is profitable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt pride.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>NEbuchadnezzars</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage had a head of gold, breſt and arms of ſilver, belly &amp; thighes of braſſe, but feet of clay.</p>
                  <p>Whatſoever thy wealth, wiſdome, birth,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:35549:99"/>beauty, ſtate or ſtrength be, thy foundation is in the duſt, <hi>Job.</hi> 4.19.</p>
                  <p>There is a great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt a Cedar and a ſhrub; a Vine and a bramble, ſo long as both grow: but cut them down, and burn them, &amp; there will be no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in their aſhes.</p>
                  <p>Cheſs-men are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed upon the boord whileſt the game is play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but being done, they are tumbled into a bag without order.</p>
                  <p>In this life ſome are
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:35549:99"/>ſet upon the throne: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are grinding at the mill.</p>
                  <p>Some are cloathed in purple, and fare delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly every day: others lie at the gates and have not ſo much as the crums of their Tables.</p>
                  <p>But in the grave rich and poor meet together, and the ulcers of <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> will make as good duſt as the paint of <hi>Jeza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saul</hi> being anointed King over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to go to <hi>Rachels</hi>
                     <pb n="190" facs="tcp:35549:100"/>ſepulchre: that the ſight of a Sepulchre might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay the haughtineſſe of his new honour, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.2.</p>
                  <p>Kings muſt pile up gaeir Crownes at the thtes of the grave, and lay down their Scepters at the feet of death.</p>
                  <p>The daughters of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, which are haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, walking with ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth necks, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton eys, mincing as they goe, and making a tink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with their feet, muſt drop into the grave,
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:35549:100"/>where in ſtead of ſweet ſmels there ſhal be ſtink: and in ſtead of well ſet hair, baldneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.16, 24.</p>
                  <p>They that glory in their Anceſtours, in the nobleneſs of their birth, and bloud, muſt make their bed in the dark, and acknowledge corruption for their father, and the Worm for their mother and ſiſter, <hi>Job</hi> 17.14.</p>
                  <p>I have ſaid, Ye are gods, and all of you are children of the moſt high: but ye ſhall die
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:35549:101"/>like men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6, 7.</p>
                  <p>Why then art thou proud, O Duſt and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes!</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Nulla diſcretio inter cada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vera mortuorum, niſi quod gravius foetent divitum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora diſtenta luxuriâ.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Amb. Hexam. l. 6. c. 8.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. II. <hi>It is profitable againſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe rich man in the Goſpel when he had built his barns, and inned his harveſt, was called away and carries nothing
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:35549:101"/>with him of all the ſtore he had provided, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>The Spider ſpins out her own bowels, to make a Cobweb, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a maid comes with a broome and ſweeps it down.</p>
                  <p>Horſes at night are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laden of their burthens, and turned into a dirty Stable with a galled back: So are rich men into the grave, and for the moſt part with a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led conſcience.</p>
                  <p>A Mill wears it ſelfe with grinding, &amp; though
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:35549:102"/>it turn about continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet it removes not out of its place.</p>
                  <p>It is but in vain for men to riſe up early, and to ſit up late, and to eat the bread of carefulneſs. For naked came I out of my mothers womb, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſhall I return thither, <hi>Job</hi> 1.21.</p>
                  <p>I hated all the labour which I had taken under the Sun, becauſe I ſhould leave it unto the man that ſhall be after me; And who knoweth whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee ſhall be a wiſe
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:35549:102"/>man or a fool? Yet ſhall he have rule over all my labour wherein I have laboured, and wherein I have ſhewed my ſelf wiſe under the Sun. This is alſo vanity, <hi>Ec.</hi> 2.18, 19</p>
                  <p>Surely every man wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in a vain ſhew, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are diſquieted in vain: he heapeth up rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and knoweth not who ſhall gather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 39.6.</p>
                  <p>We brought nothing with us into this world, and it is certain we can carry nothing out of it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.7.</p>
                  <pb n="196" facs="tcp:35549:103"/>
                  <p>Why then art thou coveteous O Duſt and Aſhes!</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Facile contemnit omnia, qui ſe ſemper cogitat moriturum,</hi> 
                     <bibl>Jeron. in Ep. ad Paulin.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. III. <hi>It is profitable against Luſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe Prodigall ſeeing many ſpectacles of mortality by reaſon of the great famine, leaves his concubines, and rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous living, and returns again to his Father, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.</p>
                  <pb n="197" facs="tcp:35549:103"/>
                  <p>One going to the ſtews meets by the way a dead corps carried to the grave: the ſight whereof made ſuch an impreſsion in him, that he goes back again; and ever after li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved chaſt and continent.</p>
                  <p>Let not ſinne raign in your mortall bodies, that ye ſhould obey it in the luſts thereof, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12.</p>
                  <p>I beſeech you as ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and pilgrims abſtain from fleſhly luſts which warre againſt the ſoul, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11.</p>
                  <p>The argument uſed by
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:35549:104"/>theſe Apoſtles to beat down in us the luſt of ſin, and the ſin of <hi>luſt,</hi> is the <hi>mortality</hi> of our bodies.</p>
                  <p>Why then art thou luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ô Duſt and Aſhes!</p>
                  <p>Thus we ſee that the meditation of death is a ſoverein antidote againſt all the evill that is in the world. For all that is in the world, is either the luſt of the fleſh, or the luſt of the eyes, or the pride of life, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Nil ſic revocat à peccato, quam frequens morti's medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Aug.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:35549:104"/>
               <head>SECTION II.</head>
               <p>THere is nothing more certain then death, yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more uncertain in the circumſtances of it. Certain it is we muſt all die, but where, when, or how we ſhall die, of all things is moſt uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="200" facs="tcp:35549:105"/>
                  <head>CAP. I. <hi>Death is certain.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ABraham</hi> the Father of the faithfull, and the friend of God, died.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iacob</hi> wreſtled with an Angel, and prevailed, yet death was too hard for him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>David</hi> was a man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods own heart, one that triumphed over ten thouſand Philiſtims, yet death triumphed over him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Solomon</hi> knew the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:35549:105"/>of all plants from the Cedar in Libanus to the hyſſope upon the wall, yet no plant had this vertue to make him immortall.</p>
                  <p>The fathers have eaten Manna, and are dead.</p>
                  <p>There is but one way into the world, but there are a thouſand out of it.</p>
                  <p>Man when he comes into the world, is like an hour-glaſſe new turned up, which never ceaſes running till it be all out.</p>
                  <p>Like <hi>Peter and Iohn,</hi> we run who ſhall firſt
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:35549:106"/>come at the Sepulchre, <hi>John</hi> 20.4.</p>
                  <p>And they that are there already, rot and crumble away to make roome for us that muſt come after them.</p>
                  <p>Duſt thou art, and to duſt ſhalt thou return, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19.</p>
                  <p>What man is he that liveth, and ſhall not ſee death? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.48.</p>
                  <p>The duſt ſhall return to the earth as it was: &amp; the ſpirit ſhall return un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God that gave it, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 12.7.</p>
                  <pb n="203" facs="tcp:35549:106"/>
                  <p>It is appointed for <hi>all</hi> men once to die. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27.</p>
                  <p>We <hi>muſt needs die,</hi> and are as water ſpilt upon the ground, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be gathered up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.14.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. II. <hi>The time uncertain.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AN infant in the wombe knows not the time when hee ſhall come into the world; and being come, knows not the time when hee ſhall go out of it.</p>
                  <pb n="204" facs="tcp:35549:107"/>
                  <p>The rich man promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf many years, but fool that he was, that night his ſoul was fetcht from him, <hi>Lu.</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>Behold now I am old and know not the day of my death, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.2.</p>
                  <p>One dieth in his full ſtrength, when his breſts are full of milk, and his bones are moiſtned with marrow, another dieth in the bitterneſſe of his ſoul, <hi>Job</hi> 21.23, 24.</p>
                  <p>Man alſo knoweth not his time; as the fiſhes that are taken in an evill net,
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:35549:107"/>and as the birds that are caught in the ſnare; ſo are the ſons of men ſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in an evil time; when it falleth ſuddenly upon them, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.12.</p>
                  <p>God would have us ignorant of the laſt day, that we might be ready every day.</p>
                  <p>Take yee heed watch and pray, for ye know notwhen the time is, <hi>Mark</hi> 13.33.</p>
                  <p>To deferre repentance then till to morrow, is very dangerous. God hath promiſed thee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:35549:108"/>if thou doſt repent to day: but if thou doſt not repent, he hath not promiſed that thou ſhalt live till to morrow.</p>
                  <p>Boaſt not thy ſelfe of to morrow, for thou knoweſt not what a day may bring forth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.1.</p>
                  <p>If not an end of thy ſins, it may be an end of thy life.</p>
                  <p>If it bring not forth <hi>converſion,</hi> it may bring forth <hi>confuſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Go to now, ye that ſay, To day, or to morrow
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:35549:108"/>we will do thus or thus: whereas ye know not what ſhall be on the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: for what is your life? It is even a vapour which appeareth for a little time, and then vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth away, <hi>I am.</hi> 4.13, 14</p>
                  <p>Whatſoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with all thy might: for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the grave, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou goeſt, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10.</p>
                  <p>We are but tenants at will, and we know not
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:35549:109"/>how ſoon our great Land-lord may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge us.</p>
                  <p>Doe therefore as the wiſe Steward, before thou beeſt turned out of this houſe, make ſure of another, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.4.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. III. <hi>The place uncertain.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>DEath ſurprized <hi>Abel</hi> when he was walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the field, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eli</hi> when he was ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at his doore, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.18.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jobs</hi> children at a feaſt, <hi>Job</hi> 1.19.</p>
                  <pb n="209" facs="tcp:35549:109"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eglon</hi> in his ſummer parlour, <hi>Judg.</hi> 3.20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Zacharias</hi> betwixt the Temple and the Altar, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.35.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Senacherib</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Niſroch</hi> his god, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37.38.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> whileſt hee ſlept in his bedchamber, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.7.</p>
                  <p>The Philiſtims whileſt they were ſporting in the Theatre, <hi>Judg.</hi> 16.30.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> whileſt he fate upon his throne, <hi>Act.</hi> 12.23.</p>
                  <p>Expect that therefore
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:35549:110"/>in every place, which in every place expects thee.</p>
                  <p>And let not the place of thy death trouble thee; for the earth is the Lords, and the fulneſſe thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. IV. <hi>The manner uncertain.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THere is a naturall death, when a man dies as a lamp goes out, becauſe there is no more oile to feed it: And there is a violent death, when the ſoul is thruſt out of doors, and the lamp of
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:35549:110"/>life not burnt, but blown out.</p>
                  <p>There is a timely death, when a man comes to his grave in his full age, as a ſhock of corn cometh in, in his ſeaſon, <hi>Job</hi> 5.26</p>
                  <p>And there is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely death, when a man is cropt as an ear of corn before it be white unto the harveſt.</p>
                  <p>There is a lingring death, when the ſoule is beſieged with ſickneſſe, and as it were ſtarved and tired out of her ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation.</p>
                  <pb n="212" facs="tcp:35549:111"/>
                  <p>And there is a ſudden death, which ſtrikes without giving warning.</p>
                  <p>There is a quiet death, a departing in peace, when the ſoul doth as it were ſteal out of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy unperceived.</p>
                  <p>And there is a death, accompanied with ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving madneſſe, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemperature. Now who knows which of theſe deaths are appointed for him?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Joſiah</hi> dies by the hurt of an arrow, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 35.23.</p>
                  <p>A Prophet of God by
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:35549:111"/>the teeth of a Lion, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.24.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abimelech</hi> by the fall of a ſtone, <hi>Judges</hi> 9.53.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jezabel</hi> is eaten up of dogs, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9.36.</p>
                  <p>Two Captains with their fifties are conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by fire from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.14.</p>
                  <p>There are ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand diſeaſes in the world, and no man in his health knows which ſhall make an end of him. For unto God the Lord belong the iſſues of death, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.20.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="214" facs="tcp:35549:112"/>
               <head>SECTION III.</head>
               <p>NOW becauſe Death is the King of terrors, and of all terrible things the moſt terrible, ſo that the very thought and remembrance of it is as bitter to fleſh and bloud, as the waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> I thought good to
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:35549:112"/>caſt in theſe Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to ſweeten it.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. I. <hi>Death is a ſleep.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SLeep is nothing elſe but a ſhort death; and death, what is it but a long ſleep?</p>
                  <p>Hence antiquity made theſe two brethen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lazarus</hi> our friend ſleepeth, <hi>John</hi> 11.11.</p>
                  <p>And when <hi>Stephen</hi> had ſaid thus, he fell aſleep, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.60.</p>
                  <pb n="216" facs="tcp:35549:113"/>
                  <p>Brethren, I would not have you ignorant concerning them that are aſleep, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.13.</p>
                  <p>The places appointed for buriall were called <hi>Coemeteries,</hi> that is, ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing places.</p>
                  <p>Now the ſleep of a labouring man is ſweet, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.12.</p>
                  <p>Lord, if he ſleep he ſhall do wel, <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.12.</p>
                  <p>Hence alſo is it that our graves are called onr beds.</p>
                  <p>They ſhall reſt in their beds, every one walking
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:35549:113"/>in his uprightneſſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jobs</hi> bed was full of toſſings to and fro, <hi>Job</hi> 7.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Davids</hi> bed was wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with tears. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 6.6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> bed affrighted him with troubleſome thoughts, fearfull dreames, and ſtrange viſions, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.5.</p>
                  <p>But this bed in the Hebrew tongue is called <hi>Dumah,</hi> becauſe it is a place of reſt, and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
                  <p>I will lay me down in
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:35549:114"/>peace and take my reſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.8.</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>In vita vigilant juſti, ideo in morte dicuntur dormire.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Aug.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. II. <hi>Death hath no ſting.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>DOgges that have no teeth may bark at us, but they cannot bite us.</p>
                  <p>Serpents that have no ſtings, may hiſſe at us, but cannot hurt us.</p>
                  <p>Bees, they ſay, when they have loſt their ſtings, become droans ever after.</p>
                  <pb n="219" facs="tcp:35549:114"/>
                  <p>Death loſt her ſting in the ſide of our Saviour, and though it ſtill leap upon us, we may ſhake it off as <hi>Paul</hi> did the viper, without hurt.</p>
                  <p>Behold, I give you power to tread on Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and Scorpions, &amp; over all the power of the enemy, and nothing ſhall by any means hurt you, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.19.</p>
                  <p>Death is ſwallowed up in victory: O death where is thy ſting?</p>
                  <p>Thanks be unto God who hath given us victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:35549:115"/>through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55, 56.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. III. <hi>Death is good for us.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WEE may ſay of death as <hi>David</hi> did of <hi>Ahimaaz,</hi> He is a good man, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth good tidings, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.27.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the death of the body frees us from the body of death, the Law of the members, the prick in the fleſh, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks of corruption.</p>
                  <pb n="221" facs="tcp:35549:115"/>
                  <p>The good which I would do, I cannot do; and the evill which I would not doe, that doe I, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.19.</p>
                  <p>I ſee a law in my mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers warring againſt the law in my minde, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23.</p>
                  <p>This makes every child of God cry out, O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me?</p>
                  <p>Why, Death doth it, for he that is dead is freed from ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.7.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it frees us from the miſeries and
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:35549:116"/>incumbrances of this life.</p>
                  <p>So many are the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and calamities of this life, that were it not for the hope of heaven, it would not be much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then hell.</p>
                  <p>Croſſes come as thick upon us, as <hi>Jobs</hi> meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
                  <p>The life of man is a winters day, very ſhort, and very cloudy.</p>
                  <p>Few and evill have the days of my life been, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.9.</p>
                  <p>Man that is born of a
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:35549:116"/>woman is of few days &amp; full of trouble; few are our days, but many our troubles, <hi>Job</hi> 14.1.</p>
                  <p>The day of death is the year of <hi>Jubilee,</hi> and frees us of all theſe evils.</p>
                  <p>There the wicked ceaſe from troubling: &amp; there the weary be at reſt.</p>
                  <p>There the Priſoners reſt together, and heare not the voice of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſour.</p>
                  <p>The ſmall and great are there: and the ſervant is free from his maſter, <hi>Job</hi> 3.17, 18, 19.</p>
                  <pb n="224" facs="tcp:35549:117"/>
                  <p>Hence the Heathen ſaid, it was the beſt thing not to be born at all, and the next to that was to die quickly.</p>
                  <p>It was the cuſtome of many nations to weep at the birth of their friends, and to rejoyce at their burials; and not unwiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſays <hi>Ambroſ. in orat. de fide reſurr.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, death (like the Angell) plucks us out of Sodom, and conducts us to Zoar, a city of refuge and ſafety.</p>
                  <p>It tranſlates us out of
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:35549:117"/>a priſon, to a Palace; from a vale of miſery, to a kingdome of glory; from Leeks and Onions, to Rivers of Milk and Honey.</p>
                  <p>From the Tents of Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar, and Tabernacles of the wicked, to mount Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the city of the living God, the heavenly Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, to an innumerable company of Angels, to the generall Aſſembly, and Church of the firſt born which are inrolled in heaven, to God the Judge of all, to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:35549:118"/>of juſt men made perfect, and to Jeſus the Mediator of the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23.</p>
                  <p>Death is like the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon gate of a city, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row which the Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor paſſes to execution, but the honeſt Citizen to his recreation.</p>
                  <p>We know that if the earthly houſe of this ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle be diſſolved, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternall in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.</p>
                  <p>Where God ſhall wipe
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:35549:118"/>away all tears from our eyes: and there ſhall be no more death, nor ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, nor crying, neither ſhall there be any more pain, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.4.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, we may with <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> praiſe the dead, that are already dead, more then the living that are yet alive, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.2.</p>
                  <p>And ſay with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> To me to live is Chriſt, and to die is gain, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="228" facs="tcp:35549:119"/>
                  <head>CAP. IV. <hi>There ſhall bee a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT troubles us not to ſee the Sun ſet, becauſe we know it will riſe again the next morning. God reſtored to <hi>Iob</hi> every thing double but his children: they were not <hi>amiſsi,</hi> but <hi>praemiſsi:</hi> not loſt, but laid up, and then ſhall be a day of reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Though after my skin, worms deſtroy this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, yet in my fleſh ſhall
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:35549:119"/>I ſee God: whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelf and mine eyes ſhall behold, and not another, though my reins be conſumed in me, <hi>Job</hi> 19.26, 27.</p>
                  <p>Thy dead men ſhall live, together with my dead body ſhall they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe: awake and ſing yee that dwell in the duſt; for thy dew is as the dew of herbs, and the Earth ſhall caſt out her dead, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.19.</p>
                  <p>So then, death is but a Parentheſis, and the ſoul and body, though diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:35549:120"/>by it, will meet again together.</p>
                  <p>Nay the body ſhall not onely ariſe, but it fares with the body as with old houſes, which being pull'd down, new ones are erected in their rooms better and more ſtately then the former.</p>
                  <p>It is ſown in corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is raiſed in incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
                  <p>It is ſown in diſhonor, it is raiſed in glory.</p>
                  <p>It is ſown in weakneſs, it is raiſed in power.</p>
                  <p>It is ſown a naturall
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:35549:120"/>body, it is raiſed a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42, 43.</p>
                  <p>Thus death like a rare Alchy miſt, diſſolves the baſe metal of our bodies, and converts it to a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ſubſtance.</p>
                  <p>The body when it rots in the grave, is as linnen worn to rags, and caſt upon the dunghill: but at the reſurrection it is like thoſe Rags gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up, and made into paper, which many times becomes gilt, and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of noble and divine impreſsions.</p>
                  <pb n="232" facs="tcp:35549:121"/>
                  <p>The fire burnt the bands of the three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but ſindged not ſo much as a haire of their heads, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.27.</p>
                  <p>Death looſes us from the bands of our ſins, but ſhall not cozen us of a nail of the hand, or an hair of the head, for all our hairs are numbred.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. V. <hi>The goodneſs of God.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SAint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> being asked by his friends whether he was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to die, anſwered he
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:35549:121"/>was not, becauſe he had a good Lord. What time I am affraid, I will truſt in thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.3.</p>
                  <p>Though I walk through the valley of the ſhadow of death, I will fear no evill, for thou art with me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4.</p>
                  <p>Into thy hands I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my ſpirit, for thou haſt redeemed it, ô Lord God of truth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.5.</p>
                  <p>He that hath created our ſouls after his own Image, and redeemed them with his owne bloud, will not refuſe
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:35549:122"/>them when they are commended and given up unto him.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Stephen</hi> was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving up the ghoſt, he ſaw the heavens opened, and the Sonne of man ſtanding at the right hand of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.56.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt who ſits at the right hand of God, was then ſaid to ſtand, to ſhew how ready he is to receive the ſouls of his ſervants.</p>
                  <p>Theſe conſiderations being applyed, and
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:35549:122"/>wrought well upon our hearts, will make us cry out with <hi>David,</hi> Oh when ſhall I come and appear before him! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.2.</p>
                  <p>O that I had wings like a dove, that I might flie hence and be at reſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.6.</p>
                  <p>Woe is me that I ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ in <hi>Meſech,</hi> that I dwell in the Tents of <hi>Kedar, Pſal.</hi> 120.5.</p>
                  <p>With old <hi>Simeon,</hi> Lord now letteſt thou thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant depart in peace ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy word, <hi>Lu.</hi> 2.29.</p>
                  <pb n="236" facs="tcp:35549:123"/>
                  <p>With <hi>Paul,</hi> I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23.</p>
                  <p>With Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> Come Lord Jeſus, come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="237" facs="tcp:35549:123"/>
               <head>SECTION IV.</head>
               <p>EVery man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires with <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> that he may dye the death of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and that his laſt end may be like his: and I cannot blame them. For to die well is a point of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt conſequence in the world, becauſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:35549:124"/>depends upon it. And as the tree fals ſo it muſt ly, whether it be to the North of Gods judgment, or to the South of his mercy, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.3.</p>
               <p>Now this work of dying well, cannot be done <hi>extempore,</hi> I have therefore in the laſt place contracted the art of dying well into a few precepts.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="239" facs="tcp:35549:124"/>
                  <head>CAP. I. <hi>Live well.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TO live well is to fear God, and to keep his Commandements, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13.</p>
                  <p>To love God and our neighbour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37.</p>
                  <p>To deny all ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, &amp; godly in this preſent world, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12.</p>
                  <p>To doe juſtly, to love mercy, and to walk hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with our God, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah</hi> 6.8.</p>
                  <pb n="240" facs="tcp:35549:125"/>
                  <p>To repent of our ſins, to beleeve in Chriſt, to keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Who ſo doth theſe things ſhall never fall, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.5.</p>
                  <p>A fair day may have a foul evening: but a good life cannot have a bad death.</p>
                  <p>Such as the premiſſes are, ſuch will be the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</p>
                  <p>It is ſaid of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that he died according to the word of the Lord, or at the mouth of the Lord, for the <hi>Hebrew</hi> will bear
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:35549:125"/>this reading: and the <hi>Chaldee</hi> paraphraſes it, He died at a kiſſe of the Lords mouth: God kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the righteous in their deaths, and as it were ſucks in thoſe ſouls which he breathed into them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.5.</p>
                  <p>Old <hi>Hilarion</hi> when he lay a dying, beſpake his ſoul in this manner. Get thee out of me, O my ſoul, get thee out of me: why feareſt thou, that haſt ſerved God almoſt this ſeventy years? <hi>Jerom in vita Hilarionis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="242" facs="tcp:35549:126"/>
                  <p>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright, for the end of that man is peace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.37.</p>
                  <p>Precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 116.15.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſed are they that die in the Lord, for they reſt from their labours, and their works follow them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. II. <hi>Particular directions.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the time of thy ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with <hi>Ezekiah</hi> call thy ſelf to an account
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:35549:126"/>for all thy ſins, mourn for them, in the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy ſoul confeſſe them to God, and ask forgiveneſſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Send for thy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. To whom, if need be, make a ſpeciall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and take along with thee the benefit of his abſolution; Whoſe ſoever ſins ye remit they are remitted unto them: and whoſe ſoever ſins ye retain, they are retained, <hi>John</hi> 20.23.</p>
                  <p>If I forgave any thing to whom I forgave it, I
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:35549:127"/>forgave it in the perſon of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, let thy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter pray over thee: Is any ſick among you? let him call for the Elders of the Church, and let them pray over him.</p>
                  <p>If he hath commited ſins, they ſhall be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.14, 15.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, let him give thee the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</p>
                  <p>This is the beſt <hi>viati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> and proviſion for ſo long a journey.</p>
                  <p>I may ſay to thee as
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:35549:127"/>the Angel to <hi>Eliah,</hi> Ariſe and eat, for the journey is too great for thee.</p>
                  <p>And if with <hi>Eliah,</hi> thou doſt eat and drink, thou maiſt travell in the ſtrength of this meat to <hi>Horeb</hi> the mount of God, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.7, 8.</p>
                  <p>This is the bread that came down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that a man may eat thereof, and not die.</p>
                  <p>Who ſo eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my bloud, hath eternall life, and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.51, 54.</p>
                  <pb n="246" facs="tcp:35549:128"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. Euſeb. hiſt. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 45.3. Set thine houſe in order, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.1.</p>
                  <p>This will not make thee die more quickly, but more quietly.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Remember the poor. When we have beene kindly entertained at a friends houſe, it is good manners to give the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſomething when we goe away.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſed is he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereth the poore, the Lord will deliver him in the time of trouble.</p>
                  <p>The Lord will ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:35549:128"/>him upon the bed of languiſhing: and will make all his bed in his ſickneſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41.1, 3.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. If thou beeſt a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or mother of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, call them before thee, and bleſſe them.</p>
                  <p>So did <hi>Jacob</hi> when he departed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.1.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Make reſtitution (if thou beeſt able) to ſuch as thou haſt wronged, and defrauded.</p>
                  <p>Without reſtitution there is no remiſſion.</p>
                  <p>Enquire with <hi>Samuel</hi> whoſe oxe thou haſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:35549:129"/>or whoſe aſſe thou haſt taken, whom thou haſt defrauded, whom thou haſt oppreſſed, or of whoſe hand thou haſt received a bribe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore it.</p>
                  <p>Send for them who have offended thee, and forgive them: and for thoſe whom thou haſt offended, and ask for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, reſign, and give over thy ſelf to God.</p>
                  <p>Behold, here I am, let the Lord do to me, as ſeemeth good to him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.26.</p>
                  <pb n="249" facs="tcp:35549:129"/>
                  <p>Not my wil, but thine be done. And if thus thou beeſt prepared at the day of death, oh well is thee, and happy ſhalt thou be, <hi>Pſal</hi> 128.2.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſed is that ſervant whom his Lord when he cometh ſhall finde thus doing, thus dying, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.46.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A ſhort prayer for a happy departure.</head>
                  <p>O Moſt glorious Lord, the GOD of the ſpirits of all fleſh, in whoſe hands are the
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:35549:130"/>times of all men, and the keys of the Grave, I moſt meekly beſeech thee of thy goodneſſe, to pardon and forgive me all my ſins, and to make me e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mindfull of my mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</p>
                  <p>Lay often before mine eyes by thy remembring ſpirit, that the days of my pilgrimage are but few and evil; that I have here no abiding and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing City; that all fleſh, and the goodlineſſe thereof is but a flower that fadeth, &amp; a ſhadow
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:35549:130"/>that vaniſheth away, that ſo numbring my days, I may apply my heart to wiſedome, and with the wiſe Virgins provide Oil in my Lamp, and make my calling and election ſure, before I go hence, &amp; be no more ſeen. And when it ſhall pleaſe thee to caſt me upon the bed of ſickneſs, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe me about with the ſorrows of the grave, I beſeech thee for thy names ſake, for thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake, for thy Son Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt his ſake, not
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:35549:131"/>to be far from me in that needfull time of trouble, when I ſhall finde heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in my fleſh, and there be none to deliver me.</p>
                  <p>But draw near unto my ſoul, and be about my bed to pardon my ſins, to pacifie my conſcience, to ſtrengthen my faith, to mitigate my pains, &amp; to receive my ſoul, when it ſhall be commended unto thee.</p>
                  <p>Receive it O God the Father, for thou haſt created it. Receive it O
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:35549:131"/>God the Son, for thou haſt redeemed it. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it O God the Holy Ghoſt, for thou haſt ſanctified it. Receive it ô holy, bleſſed and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Trinity, that being tranſlated out of this vale of miſery, it may raign with thee, one ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>living and immortall God, in the Kingdome of Glory, world without end: <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="254" facs="tcp:35549:132"/>
               <head>SECTION I. <hi>Of the day of Judgement.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>CHriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, let my Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations now paſſe, as thou thy ſelf muſt, from the day of death to the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for all men once to die, and after that to come to judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="255" facs="tcp:35549:132"/>
                  <head>CAP. I. <hi>There ſhall bee a day of Judgment.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is an Article of our faith, that CHRIST who n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w ſits at the right hand of his Father, ſhall come from thence to judg the quick and the dead.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Adam</hi> propheſied of it, ſaying, Behold, the Lord cometh with ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of his Saints;</p>
                  <p>To execute Judgment upon all, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:35549:133"/>all that are ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all their ungodly deeds which they have committed, and of all their hard ſpeeches which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken againſt h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, <hi>Iude</hi> 14, 15.</p>
                  <p>God ſhall bring every work into judgement, with every ſecret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evill, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 12.14.</p>
                  <p>I ſaw the dead, ſmall and great, ſtand before God.</p>
                  <p>The Sea gave up the
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:35549:133"/>dead which were in it: and death and hell deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered up the dead which were in them: and they were judged every man according to his works, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.13.</p>
                  <p>It is very obſervable, that all other Articles of the Creed have been op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by Heretiques ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in whole, or in part; but no Heretique denied a day of judgment. <hi>Vide Danaeum in his Cat. of hereſies againſt the Creed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this world, <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, no man can know
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:35549:134"/>love or hatred by all that is before them. For all things come alike to all: there is one event to the righteous and to the wicked, to the good and to the clean, and to the unclean: to him that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificeth, &amp; to him that ſacrificeth not; as is the good, ſo is the ſinner; &amp; he that ſweareth, as he that feareth an oath, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 9.1, 2.</p>
                  <p>Now ſhall not the Judge of all the world do right? <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.25.</p>
                  <p>There muſt be a day
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:35549:134"/>wherein the wicked ſhall be puniſhed, and the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous rewarded.</p>
                  <p>A day wherein God will put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt an Iſraelite, and an Aegyptian; betwixt a Sheep and a Goat; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt wheat and tares.</p>
                  <p>There ſhall be a day when I will make up my Jewels, and I will ſpare them as a man ſpareth his own ſon that ſerveth him.</p>
                  <p>Then ſhall ye return, and diſcern between the righteous and the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:35549:135"/>between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17, 18.</p>
                  <p>I confeſſe the wicked are ſometimes puniſhed in this world, to aſſure us there is a God; yet it is but ſometimes, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us there is a day of judgment.</p>
                  <p>Verily there is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for the righteous: verily there is a God that judgeth the earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="261" facs="tcp:35549:135"/>
                  <head>CAP. II. <hi>An Objection anſwered.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is certain that the ſoul ſo ſoon as it is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the body, is preſented to God, and receives an irrevocable doome, either of woe, or weal.</p>
                  <p>The rich man died and preſently was in hell in torments, the begger di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and was immediately carried by Angels into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.22, 23.</p>
                  <p>So that it may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded;
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:35549:136"/>What need is there of a general day of judgment, ſeeing every man is judged at the day of his death?</p>
                  <div n="1" type="answer">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1.</head>
                     <p>Every man conſiſts of a Soul, and a Body.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Soul</hi> is judged at the day of death, the <hi>Body</hi> alſo at the day of judgment.</p>
                     <p>For as theſe two doe either ſin together, or ſerve God together; ſo they ſhall either burn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, or reign toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                     <pb n="263" facs="tcp:35549:136"/>
                     <p>Every man muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the things done in his <hi>Body,</hi> according to that he hath done, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be good or bad, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.</p>
                     <p>Yet becauſe the <hi>Soul</hi> may, and often doth ſin, or ſerve God without the <hi>Body,</hi> it may in the ſtate of ſeparation be either puniſhed or rewarded, though the <hi>Body</hi> reſt in the grave.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="answer">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2.</head>
                     <p>There muſt be a general Judgment, for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of Gods Juſtice.</p>
                     <pb n="264" facs="tcp:35549:137"/>
                     <p>God diſpoſes of every man at the day of his death, &amp; that according to the rule of Juſtice; yet that which he did in ſecret, he will doe in the view of the whole world, that ſo the generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels may give this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and applauſe of his juſt proceedings:</p>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Righteous art thou, O Lord, and righteous are thy judgments.</hi> 
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.137.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="answer">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3.</head>
                     <p>There muſt be a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:35549:137"/>beſides that at the day of death, becauſe men after they be dead, may be Inſtruments, and occaſions either of vice or vertue, of ſin or the ſervice of God.</p>
                     <p>The Patriarchs, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Apoſtles, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, and Fathers of the Church are dead and gone: yet ſtill they doe good in the Church of God by their godly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, and holy wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jeroboam, Machiavel, Marcion,</hi> all Heriticks,
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:35549:138"/>and prophane perſons die, yet they poiſon the air with ill example, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked books, diveliſh prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and after their death infect poſterity for many generations.</p>
                     <p>Their word eats as doth a canker, or gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grene, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17.</p>
                     <p>Hence it is, that as there is a particular Judgment to reward the good, or puniſh the evil they have done them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their life time; ſo there ſhall be a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Judgment to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:35549:138"/>or puniſh them for that, which after their death they have occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned to be done by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>V.S. Baſil. in l. de vera virginit.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. III. <hi>The Names given to this Day.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis day is called in the Scripture, The day of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Alas, for the day: for the day of the Lord is at hand. <hi>Joel</hi> 1.15.</p>
                  <p>Your ſelves know per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly,
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:35549:139"/>that the day of the Lord ſo cometh as a thief in the night, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.2.</p>
                  <p>Looking for and haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning unto the coming of the day of GOD, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12.</p>
                  <p>This life is called <hi>Our</hi> Day.</p>
                  <p>O Jeruſalem; if thou hadſt known, at leaſt in this <hi>Thy day,</hi> the things that belong to thy peace, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.42.</p>
                  <p>For we think our <hi>own thoughts,</hi> &amp; ſpeak our <hi>own words,</hi> and doe our <hi>own pleaſure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="269" facs="tcp:35549:139"/>
                  <p>But that ſhall be the <hi>Lords day;</hi> for the lofty looks of man ſhall be humbled, &amp; the haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of men ſhal be bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down, and the <hi>Lord alone</hi> ſhall be exalted in that day, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.11.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it is called a Day of <hi>Revelation,</hi> or <hi>Opening, Rom.</hi> 2.5.</p>
                  <p>Never was there ſuch an opening, as will be at that day.</p>
                  <p>The heavens ſhall be opened, and thoſe ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting doors ſhall be lift up, that the King of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:35549:140"/>may go forth with his Angels to judge the world, and return back again with his Saints, when he hath judged it.</p>
                  <p>The Earth ſhall be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, for the ſtone ſhall be rolled from the mouth of every Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, and the graves ſhall give up their dead.</p>
                  <p>The Books ſhall be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened.</p>
                  <p>I ſaw the dead, ſmall and great, ſtand before the Lord, and the books were opened: and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther book was opened
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:35549:140"/>which was the book of life; and the dead were judged out of thoſe things which were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the books, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their works, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12.</p>
                  <p>The ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be opened.</p>
                  <p>There is nothing hid that ſhall not be manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted; neither any thing kept ſecret that ſhall not come abroad, <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.22.</p>
                  <p>In the day when God ſhall judge the <hi>ſecrets</hi> of men by Jeſus Chriſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my Goſpell, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16.</p>
                  <pb n="272" facs="tcp:35549:141"/>
                  <p>Hell ſhall be opened to receive thoſe wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, to whom it ſhall be ſaid, Goe ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the divel and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, it is called a Day of <hi>refreſhing.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent ye therefore, and be converted, that your ſins may be blotted out when the times of <hi>refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing</hi> ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19.</p>
                  <p>What a refreſhing wil it be, when our rotten,
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:35549:141"/>and worm-eaten carkaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhall riſe up in honor and in incorruption, as flowers after a long winter?</p>
                  <p>What a refreſhing wil it be, when theſe two an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient friends, the <hi>ſoul</hi> and the <hi>body,</hi> after ſo long a ſeparation ſhall imbrace, and kiſſe each other?</p>
                  <p>What a refreſhing will it be to ſee the Divel our worſt enemy, and Death our laſt enemy, caſt into the lake of fire?</p>
                  <p>What a refreſhing wil it be to ſee Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:35549:142"/>the Savior of the world, and the head of his Church, come in his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, attended with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable company of Angels?</p>
                  <p>What a refreſhing wil it be, to hear thoſe ſweet ſentences of abſolution?</p>
                  <p>Well done, good and faithfull ſervant, enter thou into thy Maſters joy.</p>
                  <p>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdome prepared for you.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, in reſpect of
<pb n="275" facs="tcp:35549:142"/>the wicked, it is called a day of <hi>wrath.</hi> After thy hardneſſe, and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent heart, thou treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt up for thy ſelf wrath againſt the day of wrath, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5.</p>
                  <p>As alſo a day of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and gloomineſſe, a day of clouds, and of thick darkneſſe, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.2.</p>
                  <p>The Sun is pleaſing to a good eye, but offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to an eye that is ill affected.</p>
                  <p>The day of judgment is a bath of refreſhing to the godly, but a burning
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:35549:143"/>Oven to the wicked:</p>
                  <p>Behold the day com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that ſhall burn as an Oven, and all the proud, yea, and all that doe wickedly, ſhall be ſtubble, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.1.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, it is called a <hi>great</hi> day. The Angels which kept not their firſt eſtate, but left their own habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, he hath reſerved in everlaſting chains of darkneſſe, unto the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Great day. Jude</hi> 6.</p>
                  <p>The Sun ſhall be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into darkneſſe, and
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:35549:143"/>the Moon into blood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that great and nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble day of the Lord come, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.20.</p>
                  <p>It is a great day indeed, ſith ſo many great and notable things ſhall be done in it.</p>
                  <p>For the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with a ſhout, with the voice of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angel, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16.</p>
                  <p>And he ſhall ſend his Angels with a <hi>great</hi> ſound of a trumpet, and they ſhall gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Elect from the
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:35549:144"/>four winds, from one end of heaven, unto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.31.</p>
                  <p>And then the heavens ſhall paſſe away with a great noiſe, and the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall melt with fervent heat, the earth alſo and the works that are therein ſhall be burnt up, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10.</p>
                  <p>How great a day muſt that needs be, wherein the accompts and recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of all Days muſt be audited and caſt up?</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, it is commonly and uſually called the
<pb n="279" facs="tcp:35549:144"/>Day of <hi>Judgment,</hi> for it is the generall Aſſiſe wherein every man muſt be arraigned, and hold up his hand at the barre.</p>
                  <p>Both old men and maidens: young men and children.</p>
                  <p>Kings of the earth, and all people: Princes, and all Judges of the earth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECTION II.</head>
               <p>THus having ſeen that there ſhall be not only a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular,
<pb n="280" facs="tcp:35549:145"/>but a generall judgement alſo, let us in the next place inquire <hi>who</hi> &amp; what manner of Judg he is, who ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the ſentence of life, or death up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. I. <hi>Chriſt is the Judge.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is true that the whole Trinity ſhall judge us: for ſo great an action cannot paſſe without the
<pb n="281" facs="tcp:35549:145"/>conſent and authority of the three Perſons.</p>
                  <p>Yet it is aſcribed to Chriſt in reſpect of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate execution.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall appear viſibly in his humane nature, &amp; give the ſentence.</p>
                  <p>The Father judgeth no man, but hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all judgment to the <hi>Son, John</hi> 5.22.</p>
                  <p>He hath appointed a day wherein he will judg the world in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by that <hi>man</hi> whom he hath ordained, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.31.</p>
                  <pb n="282" facs="tcp:35549:146"/>
                  <p>We ſhall all ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judgment ſeat of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.10.</p>
                  <p>So that where Chriſt ſayes, he came not to judg the world, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.47. underſtand it of his firſt, not of his ſecond coming.</p>
                  <p>Fit it is that Chriſt ſhould judg the world who was judged by it: that ſo once in this world, he may ſhew his power, and Majeſty, in the ſight of all his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, eſpecially of <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate, Annas, Caia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas,</hi>
                     <pb n="283" facs="tcp:35549:146"/>and the Jews, who condemned and crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him.</p>
                  <p>They ſhall look upon me whom they have pierced, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10.</p>
                  <p>Fit it is, that Men ſhould be judged by one that is a Man.</p>
                  <p>The comfort that we have againſt the terrors of this day is, that we ſhall be judged by the Man Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
                  <p>One man is a God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another. Fear not, I am your brother <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="284" facs="tcp:35549:147"/>
                  <head>CAP. II. <hi>Chriſt a ſevere Judge.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>CHriſt in his firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was a Lambe, but in his ſecond he ſhall be a Lion.</p>
                  <p>His fan is in his hand; and he will throng hly purge his floor, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his wheat into his garner, but will burn up the chaff with unquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fire, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.12.</p>
                  <p>Hence it is that the very beſt of the Saints tremble at the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this day.</p>
                  <pb n="285" facs="tcp:35549:147"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>David</hi> was a man after Gods own heart: yet,</p>
                  <p>My fleſh trembleth for fear of thee: I am afraid of thy <hi>judgments, Pſal.</hi> 119.120.</p>
                  <p>Enter not into <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> with thy ſervant, ô Lord, for in thy ſight ſhall no man living be juſtified, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Job</hi> was a man emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for all graces: yet he ſtood amazed at the conſideration of this Iudge.</p>
                  <p>Whom though I were righteous, I would not
<pb n="286" facs="tcp:35549:148"/>anſwer: but I would make ſupplication to my <hi>Iudg, Iob</hi> 9.15.</p>
                  <p>What ſhall I do when God riſeth up? &amp; when he viſiteth, what ſhall I anſwer him? <hi>Iob</hi> 31.14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> was a choſen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, one that knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by himſelf yet ſays he, I am not thereby ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, for it is the Lord that judges me. And the Lord judges not as a man judges, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.</p>
                  <p>S. <hi>Ierome</hi> confeſſeth that his whole body trembled ſo oft as hee
<pb n="287" facs="tcp:35549:148"/>thought upon this day.</p>
                  <p>The righteous ſhall ſcarcely be ſaved, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.18.</p>
                  <p>Many there are who paſſe currant in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the world; who when they ſhal be weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Chriſts</hi> ballances will be found too light. Good reaſon then hath every man to pray as the Church teaches him; In the day of <hi>Judgement</hi> good Lord deliver me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="288" facs="tcp:35549:149"/>
                  <head>CAP. III. <hi>Chriſt an upright Judge.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HEE ſhall judge the world in <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> he ſhall miniſter judgment to the people in <hi>uprighteneſs, Pſal.</hi> 9.8.</p>
                  <p>The Lord cometh to judge the earth: with <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> ſhall he judg the world, and the people with <hi>equity, Pſal.</hi> 98.9.</p>
                  <p>Henceforth there is laid up for me a crown of righteouſneſſe, which the Lord the <hi>righteous</hi>
                     <pb n="289" facs="tcp:35549:149"/>Iudge ſhall give me at that day, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</p>
                  <p>The Iudges of the earth may abſolve the guilty, and condemn the innocent, being corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted By fear:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pilate</hi> for the fear of <hi>Caeſar</hi> condemned Chriſt, whom the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence pronounced inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</p>
                  <p>But this judge cannot be thus corrupted: for,</p>
                  <p>Whom ſhall he fear, that is omnipotent? or of whom ſhall he be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid,
<pb n="290" facs="tcp:35549:150"/>that ſhal come with great power and glory? <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.26.</p>
                  <p>Or they may be corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted with their own affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of love, or hatred. <hi>Herod</hi> adjudges <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> to death, for the love of <hi>Herodias</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren caſt him into the pit becauſe they hated him, <hi>Ge.</hi> 37.4.</p>
                  <p>But this Judg cannot be thus corrupted: for,</p>
                  <p>He is no accepter of perſons, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.34.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall not judg af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="291" facs="tcp:35549:150"/>the ſight of his eyes, but with righteouſneſſe ſhall he judge his people, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.3, 4.</p>
                  <p>He will render to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man according to his deeds, whether Iew or Gentile, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6.9.</p>
                  <p>Or they may be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with bribes: <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thro</hi> well adviſed <hi>Moſes</hi> to chuſe ſuch men for <hi>Judges</hi> as hated cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt not wreſt judgment, thou ſhalt not reſpect perſons, neither take a gift: for a gift
<pb n="292" facs="tcp:35549:151"/>doth blind the eyes of the wiſe, and pervert the words of the righteous, <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.19.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt our Iudge can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo corrupted.</p>
                  <p>If he would take a bribe, thou ſhalt have none to give him at that day.</p>
                  <p>But if thou couldeſt give him the Kingdoms of the world, &amp; the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them, he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe; for he is the Lord of lords, a great God, a mighty, and a terrible, which regardeth not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="293" facs="tcp:35549:151"/>nor taketh reward, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.17.</p>
                  <p>A good <hi>conſcience</hi> wil doe us more good then, then a full <hi>purſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Riches</hi> profit not in the day of wrath, but <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> delivereth from death, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.4.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. IV. <hi>Chriſt an All knowing Judge.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AS his uprightneſſe is ſuch that he cannot be corrupted, ſo his <hi>knowledge</hi> is ſuch that
<pb n="294" facs="tcp:35549:152"/>he cannot be deceived.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall not reprove after the hearing of his ears, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.3.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall not judge us according to the report and teſtimony of others which is uncertain, but according to his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitive knowledg, which is infallible.</p>
                  <p>Come and ſee a man which told me all the things that ever I did: Is not this the Chriſt? <hi>John</hi> 4.29.</p>
                  <p>Neither is there any creature that is not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt
<pb n="295" facs="tcp:35549:152"/>in his ſight: but all things are naked, &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto the eyes of him with whom we have to do, <hi>Heb</hi> 4.13.</p>
                  <p>The word in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall imports ſuch an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penneſs, as when the skin is pulled off, &amp; the back chined down, ſo that the very entrails, and moſt ſecret paſſages of nature may be diſcerned.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things haſt thou done, and I kept ſilence, thou thoughteſt I was altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelf, but I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
<pb n="296" facs="tcp:35549:153"/>thee, and ſet them in order before thine eys, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21.</p>
                  <p>Hence it is that he is ſaid to keep a book of remembrance by him, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16.</p>
                  <p>Some ſins are ſaid to be ſecret in reſpect of him that commits them. Who can underſtand his errours?</p>
                  <p>Cleanſe thou me from my <hi>ſecret</hi> faults, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 19.12</p>
                  <p>Or in reſpect of the world. The Adulterer eats his pleaſant bread in <hi>ſecret, Prov.</hi> 9.17.</p>
                  <pb n="297" facs="tcp:35549:153"/>
                  <p>But no ſins are ſecret in reſpect of God: for,</p>
                  <p>He ſets our iniquities before him: even our <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret</hi> ſins in the ſight of his countenance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.8.</p>
                  <p>At that day then in vain will it be for us to deny the fact, or to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe it, or to ſhift and transferre it from one to another: for,</p>
                  <p>The Lord ſeeth not as man ſeeth, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="298" facs="tcp:35549:154"/>
                  <head>CAP. V. <hi>Chriſt is an inexorable Judg.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AS this Iudge cannot be corrupted, nor deceived; ſo neither can he be intreated: Now is the accepted time, now is the day of ſalvation, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2.</p>
                  <p>Seek the Lord whilſt he may be found, call upon him whilſt he is near, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.6.</p>
                  <p>That is a time of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and though we cry as loud as thunder,
<pb n="299" facs="tcp:35549:154"/>he will not hear us, though we cut our ſelves with lancers, as <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, till the blood guſh out, he will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard us.</p>
                  <p>Wil God hear his cry when trouble cometh upon him? <hi>Job</hi> 27.9.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe I have called and ye refuſed, I have ſtretched out my hand, and no man regarded:</p>
                  <p>I alſo will laugh at your calamity, and mock when your fear cometh.</p>
                  <p>Then ſhall they call upon me, but I will not
<pb n="300" facs="tcp:35549:155"/>anſwer: they ſhall ſeek me early, but they ſhall not find me, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24, 26, 28.</p>
                  <p>The fooliſh Virgins knock at the door of mercy, but it is ſhut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.11.</p>
                  <p>Then will I profeſſe unto them, I never knew you: depart from me ye that work iniquity, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.23.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="301" facs="tcp:35549:155"/>
               <head>SECTION III.</head>
               <p>HAving now ſeen who, and what manner of Judge thou ſhalt have, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him now ſet upon the judgment ſeat attended with his glorious Angels, and calling thee up to anſwer theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatories.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="302" facs="tcp:35549:156"/>
                  <head>CAP. I. <hi>Who art thou?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TO this thy anſwer wil be that thou art a <hi>Man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> reply unto thee, If a man, ſhew me my Image wherein I created thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caeſars</hi> peny was known by <hi>Caeſars</hi> Image, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaw the coat of his ſon <hi>Joſeph,</hi> It is my ſons coat, ſays he, but an evil beaſt hath devoured him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.33.</p>
                  <pb n="303" facs="tcp:35549:156"/>
                  <p>So Chriſt will ſay to us at the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, This is the face and figure of a man, but an evil beaſt hath devoured my Image.</p>
                  <p>The Drunkard hath loſt the Image of God, and laid a ſwine in the room of it.</p>
                  <p>The Covetous hath loſt the Image of God, and laid a <hi>ravenous wolf</hi> in the room of it.</p>
                  <p>The Adulterer hath loſt the Image of God, and laid a <hi>goat</hi> or an <hi>horſe</hi> in the room of it.</p>
                  <pb n="304" facs="tcp:35549:157"/>
                  <p>The crafty and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious perſon, hath loſt the Image of God, and laid a <hi>fox</hi> and a <hi>dog</hi> in the room of it.</p>
                  <p>They have corrupted themſelves, and their ſpot is not the ſpot of his children, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.5.</p>
                  <p>Man that is in honour and underſtandeth not, may be compared to the beaſts that periſh, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.20.</p>
                  <p>And no beaſt ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the new Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem: for</p>
                  <p>Without are dogs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="305" facs="tcp:35549:157"/>
                  <head>CAP. II. <hi>Of what Religion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">The next Interrogatory will be, Of what Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on art thou?</head>
                  <p>TO paſſe by Turks, Iewes, Infidels, thy anſwer will be, <hi>I am a Christian.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jacob</hi> profeſſes to his Father, that he was his very ſon <hi>Eſau,</hi> and yet was not.</p>
                  <p>The Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> had a name to be alive, yet was dead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1.</p>
                  <p>Many ſhall ſay at that
<pb n="306" facs="tcp:35549:158"/>day, Lord, Lord, we have been baptized in thy Name, we have called upon thy Name, we have propheſied in thy Name, who notwithſtanding are workers of iniquity.</p>
                  <p>A <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is a name of <hi>Duty,</hi> as well as of <hi>Dignity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You are my <hi>Friends</hi> if you doe whatſoever I command you, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.14</p>
                  <p>By this ſhall all men know that you are my <hi>Diſciples,</hi> if ye love one another, <hi>Iohn</hi> 13.35.</p>
                  <p>As many of you as
<pb n="307" facs="tcp:35549:158"/>have been baptized into <hi>Chriſt,</hi> have put on <hi>Chriſt, Gal.</hi> 3.27.</p>
                  <p>They that are <hi>Chriſts,</hi> have crucified the fleſh, with the affections and luſts, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24.</p>
                  <p>Art thou a Chriſtian, who haſt taken the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt and made them the members of an harlot? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15.</p>
                  <p>Art thou a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> who haſt ſeen <hi>Chriſt</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, &amp; haſt not clothed him: hungry, and haſt not fed him: thirſty, and haſt given him no drink:
<pb n="308" facs="tcp:35549:159"/>ſick, and in priſon, and haſt not viſited him.</p>
                  <p>In a word, art thou a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> that haſt lived in the practice of groſſe and known ſins?</p>
                  <p>What Communion is there betwixt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Belial,</hi> betwixt light and darkneſſe, betwixt righteouſneſſe &amp; unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15.</p>
                  <p>The Jews boaſted they were the children of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> but <hi>Chriſt</hi> tels them they were the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Divell, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did his works, <hi>John</hi> 8.44.</p>
                  <pb n="309" facs="tcp:35549:159"/>
                  <p>If thou beeſt not a true, but a titular <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> having a form of godlineſſe, but not the power of it, thy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wil be more heavy, and intolerable, then that of Turks and Infidels.</p>
                  <p>The Servant that knows his Maſters will, and does it not, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes.</p>
                  <p>Unto whomſoever much is given, of him ſhall much be required, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.47, 48.</p>
                  <p>Verily I ſay unto you,
<pb n="310" facs="tcp:35549:160"/>it ſhall be more tolerable for Sodom and Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah at the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then for you, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.15.</p>
                  <p>It had been better for them not to have known the way of righteouſneſs, then after they have known it, to turn from the holy commandment delivered unto them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21.</p>
                  <p>I therefore beſeech you to walk worthy of the vocation wherewith ye are called, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.1.</p>
                  <p>And let every one that
<pb n="311" facs="tcp:35549:160"/>nameth the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> depart from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19.</p>
                  <p>And let us pray as our Church teaches us in the Collect for the third Sunday after Eaſter:</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                     <body>
                        <p>ALmighty God, &amp;c. Grant unto all them that be admitted into the fellowſhip of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that they may eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew thoſe things that be contrary to their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, and follow all ſuch things as be agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the ſame, through
<pb n="312" facs="tcp:35549:161"/>our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. III. <hi>Of what Profeſsion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe next Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory will be the ſame that the Marriners put to <hi>Jonas.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What is thine occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Jonah</hi> 1.8.</p>
                  <p>Art thou a Magiſtrate? <hi>Supreme,</hi> an Emperour, King &amp;c. or <hi>ſubordinate,</hi> an inferiour officer, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;</p>
                  <pb n="313" facs="tcp:35549:161"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> if thou haſt maintained Gods true Religion, and beene a nurſing Father to the Church, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.23.</p>
                  <p>If thou haſt rooted out Hereſie, Idolatry, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 15.12.</p>
                  <p>If thou haſt provided Miniſters to inſtruct the people, and maintenance for thoſe Miniſters.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> ſent the Prieſts, and Levites, and the Book of the Law of the Lord with them, and they went about throughout all the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="314" facs="tcp:35549:162"/>of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and taught the people, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.9.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hezekiah</hi> commanded the people that dwelt in Jeruſalem, to give the portion of the Prieſts, &amp; the Levites, that they might be encouraged in the Law of the Lord, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.4.</p>
                  <p>If thou haſt built, and repaired the houſe of God, and places of his worſhip, as did <hi>Solomon, Joſiah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> if thou haſt been an example of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and godlineſſe to thy people.</p>
                  <pb n="315" facs="tcp:35549:162"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>David</hi> himſelf dances before the Ark, and the houſe of Iſrael follow him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.14.</p>
                  <p>The King of Ninivie was the firſt that hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf in ſackcloth and aſhes, and then the inhabitants of the City did likewiſe.</p>
                  <p>Examples of great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages have a ſtrong <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence,</hi> nay, as it were a <hi>violence</hi> upon inferiors.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caeſar</hi> filled the Empire with Soldiers, <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> with Scholars, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> if they have
<pb n="316" facs="tcp:35549:163"/>provided good Laws, &amp; executed them, that ſuch as live under them may be godly and quietly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned.</p>
                  <p>Good Laws are ſuch as are agreeable to the Law of Nature, and the word of God.</p>
                  <p>And they are then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, when great flies are taken as well as ſmall ones.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> if thou haſt puniſhed the wicked, and cheriſhed the good.</p>
                  <p>Mine eyes ſhall be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the faithfull of the
<pb n="317" facs="tcp:35549:163"/>Land, that they may dwell with me; he that walketh in a perfect way, ſhall be my ſervant:</p>
                  <p>But I will early de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the wicked of the Land, that I may cut off all wicked doers from the City of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.6, 8.</p>
                  <p>Kings and Governors are ſent by God for the puniſhment of evill do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and for the praiſe of them that doe well, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14.</p>
                  <p>It cannot be wel then if <hi>Crows</hi> be pardoned &amp; <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons</hi> puniſhed.</p>
                  <pb n="318" facs="tcp:35549:164"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fiftly,</hi> if thou haſt heard the cries of the poor, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their petitions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed their wrongs.</p>
                  <p>Defend the poor and fatherleſſe: do juſtice to the afflicted and needy.</p>
                  <p>Deliver the poor, and needy: rid them out of the hand of the wicked, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.3, 4.</p>
                  <p>Be wiſe now therefore O ye kings: be inſtructed ye that are Judges of the earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.10.</p>
                  <p>Remember there will be <hi>Deus &amp; dies ultionis,</hi> A God, and a day of vengeance.</p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb n="319" facs="tcp:35549:164"/>
                     <head>But art thou a Miniſter?</head>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> if thou didſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in at the doore, or climb in at the window; if thou wert called of God, or intrudeſt thy ſelf.</p>
                     <p>A man may know if he be called of God, by thoſe talents which are committed to him.</p>
                     <p>It is required that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Miniſter have <hi>ſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am competentem,</hi> if not <hi>eminentem;</hi> that is, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent,</hi> though not <hi>emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent</hi> knowledge.</p>
                     <pb n="320" facs="tcp:35549:165"/>
                     <p>For the Prieſts lips muſt keep knowledge, &amp; the people muſt ſeek it at his lips, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> if thou haſt taught and inſtructed the people committed to thee.</p>
                     <p>Feed my ſheep, <hi>John</hi> 21.16.</p>
                     <p>I have not ſhunned to declare unto you all the counſell of God.</p>
                     <p>Take heed therefore unto your ſelves, and to all the flock, over the which the Lord hath made you overſeers, to
<pb n="321" facs="tcp:35549:165"/>feed the Church of God, which he hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with his own Blood, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.27, 28.</p>
                     <p>It is required of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter that he be διδακτικὸς, apt and able to teach, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24.</p>
                     <p>He that is <hi>ignorant</hi> and cannot teach, is a dumb <hi>dog.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He that can and will not, is a dumb <hi>Divel,</hi> (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs lawfully detained.)</p>
                     <p>Where no viſion is there the people periſh, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.18.</p>
                     <p>His bloud will I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="322" facs="tcp:35549:166"/>at thy hand, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.6.</p>
                     <p>Who then is a faithfull and wiſe ſervant, whom his Lord hath made ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler over all his houſhold to give them meat in due ſeaſon?</p>
                     <p>Bleſſed is that ſervant whom his Lord, when he cometh ſhall find <hi>ſo</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.45, 46.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> if thy life hath agreed with thy Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
                     <p>He that was miſ-ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, or had any blemiſh, might not come nigh to
<pb n="323" facs="tcp:35549:166"/>offer the offerings of the Lord, <hi>Lev.</hi> 21.21.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Moſes</hi> when he bleſſes the tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> deſires of God, that his <hi>Thum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mim</hi> and <hi>Urim</hi> might be with his Holy One, <hi>i.e.</hi> integrity of <hi>life,</hi> as well as the light of <hi>Learning, Deut.</hi> 33.8.</p>
                     <p>It is ſaid of Chriſt, that he was a Prophet mighty in <hi>deed</hi> and <hi>word,</hi> before God, and all the people, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.19.</p>
                     <p>Thou that teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf? thou that
<pb n="324" facs="tcp:35549:167"/>preacheſt a man ſhould not ſteal, doſt thou ſteal?</p>
                     <p>Thou that ſayeſt, a man ſhould not commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, doſt thou commit adultery? thou that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreſt Idols, doſt thou commit ſacriledg? <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.21, 22.</p>
                     <p>Be thou an example of the beleevers, in word, in converſation, in charity, in purity, in ſpirit, in faith, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Or, art thou an Officer?</head>
                     <p>Thou ſhall be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</p>
                     <p>If thou haſt not exacted
<pb n="325" facs="tcp:35549:167"/>more then was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for thee, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.13.</p>
                     <p>If thou haſt not dealt with the poor, as the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of <hi>Elies</hi> ſons did,</p>
                     <p>If thou wilt not give it me, I will take it by force, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.16.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Or, art thou a Souldier?</head>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</p>
                     <p>If thou haſt done vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to no man:</p>
                     <p>If thou haſt not accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed any falſly:</p>
                     <p>If thou haſt been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with thy wages, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.14.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb n="326" facs="tcp:35549:168"/>
                     <head>Or, art thou a tradeſman?</head>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</p>
                     <p>If thou haſt not uſed falſe weights, deceitfull ballances, unjuſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; all which are an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination to the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.10.</p>
                     <p>If thou haſt not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times taken the name of God in vain, to obtrude a bad commodity upon thy neighbour: <hi>&amp; ſic de caeteris.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I may now ſay of our Judg, as <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſons ſaid of the Governor of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="327" facs="tcp:35549:168"/>
                     <p>The man asked us <hi>ſtraitly</hi> of our ſtate, <hi>Gen.</hi> 43.7.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECTION IV.</head>
               <p>WE have now ſeene how Chriſt will proceed with us in the day Judgment, let us in the next place conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that final and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>revocable Sentence which ſhal paſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and it is either
<pb n="328" facs="tcp:35549:169"/>the Sentence of <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution,</hi> or <hi>Condemnation</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The ſentence of Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
                  <p>THe ſentence of <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution</hi> ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced in theſe words:</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom prepared for you from the foundation of the world,</hi> 
                     <bibl>Mat 25.34.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>In which ſentence there is not a word, a ſyllable, a letter, but is <hi>muſick</hi> to the care, <hi>hony</hi> to the
<pb n="329" facs="tcp:35549:169"/>mouth, and a <hi>Jubilee</hi> to the heart.</p>
                  <p>How wil our ears be raviſhed, and our hearts dance within us, to hear Chriſt pronounce us the <hi>bleſſed ones of his Father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To hear that ſweet cal &amp; invitation, <hi>Come ye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To hear the glory of that inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to which we muſt come;
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Kingdome,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Kingdome,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Prepared for us of old.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Bleſſed are the people that ſhall hear this joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſound, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="330" facs="tcp:35549:170"/>
                  <head>CAP. II. <hi>The ſentence of Abſolution ſhall be firſt pronounced.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE good Servant was rewarded &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into his Maſters joy: and then the evil &amp; unprofitable ſervant was puniſhed and caſt into utter darkneſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</p>
                  <p>They on the right hand are called to a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: and then they on the left are caſt into fire, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</p>
                  <p>God will not caſt the wicked into hell, till they
<pb n="331" facs="tcp:35549:170"/>have ſeen ſomething of the happineſſe of the Saints, which increaſeth their grief and torment.</p>
                  <p>The wicked ſhall ſee it, &amp; be grieved, he ſhall gnaſh with his teeth, and melt away, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.10.</p>
                  <p>Or, elſe, it may bee, <hi>Chriſt</hi> begins with the ſentence of <hi>Abſolution,</hi> to ſhew that he had rather <hi>ſave</hi> us, then <hi>damn</hi> us.</p>
                  <p>He is ſlow to anger, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.8.</p>
                  <p>A God that delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not in the death of a ſinner.</p>
                  <pb n="332" facs="tcp:35549:171"/>
                  <p>His own nature inclines him to ſave us, our ſins urge and provoke him to damne us.</p>
                  <p>Therefore if he muſt puniſh, he comes as it were unwillingly to it, and reſerves it for the laſt place.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. III. <hi>The ſentence of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe ſentence of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation</hi> ſhal be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced in theſe words:</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Depart from me ye cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, into everlaſting fire,
<pb n="333" facs="tcp:35549:171"/>prepared for the Divel, &amp; his angels,</hi> 
                     <bibl>Mat. 25.41.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>Not a word in this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, but is a wound; not a ſyllable, but is a ſword piercing the heart; not a letter, but is as loud and terrible as a clap of thunder.</p>
                  <p>How ſhall the loyns of the wicked tremble, and their joynts be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; their knees knock together, to hear Chriſt pronounce them curſed?</p>
                  <p>Curſed, becauſe of the puniſhment of <hi>loſſe, Depart ye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="334" facs="tcp:35549:172"/>
                  <p>There is their baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; excluſion from him, who is the fountain of life, the light of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and in whoſe preſence there is fulneſſe of joy.</p>
                  <p>Curſed becauſe of the puniſhment of <hi>Senſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Depart ye into <hi>fire,</hi> there is the extremity.</p>
                  <p>Into fire <hi>everlaſting.</hi> there is the eternity.</p>
                  <p>Prepared for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel and his Angels, there is their <hi>Company.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Immediately after theſe ſentences are pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, ſhall follow execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <pb n="335" facs="tcp:35549:172"/>
                  <p>The wicked ſhall goe away into everlaſting pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: but the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous into life eternall, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.46.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECTION V.</head>
               <p>IT remains now in the laſt place to view the uſe and influence which the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this great day of the Lord ought to have upon our affections. It is
<pb n="336" facs="tcp:35549:173"/>matter of terrour to ſome, of comfort to others, but of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to all.</p>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. I. <hi>Terrour to the wicked.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AS <hi>Paul</hi> reaſoned of righteouſneſſe, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, and judgment to come, Felix <hi>trembled, Acts</hi> 24.25.</p>
                  <p>The Jews fell back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward when they came to apprehend Chriſt in the days of his humility: how then ſhal they ſtand
<pb n="337" facs="tcp:35549:173"/>before him when he ſhal come in glory and maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty?</p>
                  <p>How terrible muſt this day needs be: when,</p>
                  <p>The mountaines ſhall quake at him, and the hills melt, and the earth bee burnt up at his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, yea the world, and all that dwell therein?</p>
                  <p>Who can ſtand before his indignation? and who can abide the fierceneſſe of his anger? his fury is poured out like fire, and the rocks are throwne down by him, <hi>Nah.</hi> 1.5, 6.</p>
                  <pb n="338" facs="tcp:35549:174"/>
                  <p>What a hard diſtreſſe ſhall the wicked be in, when they ſhall have</p>
                  <p>On one ſide their ſins accuſing.</p>
                  <p>On the other the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of <hi>God</hi> terrifying.</p>
                  <p>The gulf of hell ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping under them.</p>
                  <p>An angry Judge frowning over them.</p>
                  <p>Within them a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſtinging.</p>
                  <p>Without them the world burning? <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Surely the Kings of the earth, and the great
<pb n="339" facs="tcp:35549:174"/>men, and the rich men, and the chief Captains, and the mighty men, and every bondman, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very free man, ſhall hide themſelves in the dens and in the rocks of the mountains; and ſhall ſay to the mountains, and rocks, fall on us, and hide us from the face of him that ſitteth on the throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb.</p>
                  <p>For the great day of his wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand? <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.15, 16, 17.</p>
                  <pb n="340" facs="tcp:35549:175"/>
                  <p>Rejoyce ô young man in thy youth, and let thy heart chear thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thine own heart, &amp; in the ſight of thine eyes: but know thou, that for all theſe things God will bring thee to <hi>judgment, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 11.9.</p>
                  <p>O conſider this, you that forget God, leſt he tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver you, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.22.</p>
                  <p>Knowing the terrors of the Lord, we perſwade men, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="341" facs="tcp:35549:175"/>
                  <head>CAP. II. <hi>Comfort to the godly.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THen ſhall they ſee the Son of man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a cloud with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and great glory.</p>
                  <p>And when theſe things begin to come to paſſe, then look up, and lift up your heads, for your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption draweth nigh, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.27, 28.</p>
                  <p>The Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with a ſhout; with the voice of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angell, and with the
<pb n="342" facs="tcp:35549:176"/>trump of God, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Wherfore comfort ye one another with theſe words, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16, 17.</p>
                  <p>When Chriſt aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the Angels comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Diſciples in this manner:</p>
                  <p>This ſame Jeſus which is taken up from you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heaven, ſhall ſo come in like manner as ye have ſeen him go into heaven, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.11.</p>
                  <p>Hence it is, that the righteous are ſaid to love the day of his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, for then they
<pb n="343" facs="tcp:35549:176"/>ſhall receive a crown of righteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</p>
                  <p>The Lord is good, a ſtrong hold in the day of trouble, and he knoweth them that truſt in him, <hi>Nahum</hi> 1.7.</p>
                  <p>But of this we have heard before, where this day in reſpect of the godly is called a day of refreſhing &amp; redemption.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CAP. III. <hi>Inſtruction to all.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IF it be thus, what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men ought we to be in all holy converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="344" facs="tcp:35549:177"/>on and godlineſs? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11.</p>
                  <p>That which raiſed up the ſoul of S. <hi>Jerome</hi> to ſuch a pitch of devotion, was the continuall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of this day.</p>
                  <p>Whether I eat or drink, or whatſoever I do, me thinks I hear the laſt trump ſounding in my ears, <hi>Ariſe ye dead, and come to judgment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count not only for our preſumptuous ſins, but for our ſmalleſt ſins.</p>
                  <p>I ſay unto you, That
<pb n="345" facs="tcp:35549:177"/>of every idle word that men ſhal ſpeak, they ſhall give account thereof at the day of judgment, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.36.</p>
                  <p>We ſhall reckon not only for our own ſins, but for the ſins of others, which we have occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by our command, company, counſell, or ill example.</p>
                  <p>We ſhall reckon for the talents of grace and nature: and for the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous time afforded to us.</p>
                  <p>Hear the end of all, fear God, and keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,
<pb n="346" facs="tcp:35549:178"/>for God will bring every work in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Judgment, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13, 14.</p>
                  <p>Abound in the works of mercy and charity, for according to them wee ſhall be judged, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. Judge your ſelves here, &amp; you ſhall not be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hereafter, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31.</p>
                  <p>As for the time when, or the place where the Judgment ſeat of Chriſt ſhall be erected,</p>
                  <p>O my ſoul enter not into theſe ſecrets.</p>
                  <p>Such knowledg is too
<pb n="347" facs="tcp:35549:178"/>wonderfull for thee.</p>
                  <p>Secret things belong to the Lord our God, and revealed things to us and our children.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A ſhort Prayer for the day of Judgment.</head>
                  <p>O Moſt bleſſed Lord Jeſus, who now ſitteſt at the right hand of God the Father, and from thence ſhalt come to judg both the quick and the dead, in power and great glory; I confeſs and acknowledge, that ſuch
<pb n="348" facs="tcp:35549:179"/>is the hainouſneſſe of my ſins, the guiltineſſe of my Conſcience, and the dreadfulneſs of that day, that my very fleſh trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth, and my heart mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth within me, when I conſider that I muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the tribunall of thy juſt Judgment to give an account of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever I have done in the fleſh, whether good or evil. I know ô Lord, that if thou ſhalt enter into Judgment with me, I cannot be juſtified in thy ſight: and if thou ſhalt
<pb n="349" facs="tcp:35549:179"/>be extreme to mark what amiſſe hath paſſed from me, I ſhall not be able to anſwer thee one for a thouſand.</p>
                  <p>I appeal therefore, from the bar of thy juſtice, to the bowels of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, beſeeching thee in that day to deal with the ſoul of thy ſervant, not as a ſevere Judge, but as a mercifull Jeſus.</p>
                  <p>It will be O Lord a day of wrath, but gather me under the ſhadow of thy wings, untill the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation be paſt over.</p>
                  <pb n="350" facs="tcp:35549:180"/>
                  <p>It will be a day of darkneſſe, &amp; of gloomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: but lift thou up the light of thy countenance upon me, and I ſhall be ſaved.</p>
                  <p>It will be a day of Judgment; but in that day by thine agony and bloody paſsion, and by whatſoever thou haſt done, or ſuffered for me, good Lord deliver me.</p>
                  <p>And to this end, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee give me grace to live ſoberly, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and godly in this preſent world; to keep a
<pb n="351" facs="tcp:35549:180"/>good conſcience void of offence towards thee my God, and towards all men; to abound always in the works of charity, and mercy; and to judg and condemn my ſelf here, that I may not be condemned hereafter. That ſo whenſoever this day ſhall ſeiſe upon me, I may not be bound up with the bundle of tares which ſhall be caſt into unquenchable fire, but gathered with the wheat into thy garners, and ſet with the ſheep upon thy
<pb n="352" facs="tcp:35549:181"/>right hand, and called in the number of thoſe bleſſed ones to inherit a Kingdom, &amp; that Crown of righteouſneſſe which thou haſt purchaſed, and prepared for all thoſe that love and expect that day of thy appearing. Now unto thee ô Chriſt, together with thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; thy bleſſed Spirit, be aſcribed all power, &amp; praiſe, dignity and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="353" facs="tcp:35549:181"/>
               <head>A PRAYER FOR the Morning.</head>
               <p>OEternall and moſt glorious Lord God, and in Ieſus Chriſt our merciful and loving Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we thine unworthy creatures ſinful duſt and aſhes, are here in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility of ſouls &amp; bodies proſtrate at the loweſt footſtool of thy glorious Majeſty: beſeeching thee to bow down thine ears unto our prayers, and to open thine eyes upon our ſupplication; who from
<pb n="354" facs="tcp:35549:182"/>the ground &amp; bottom of our hearts, do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and confeſs that we have been unprofitable ſervants, prodigall chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, &amp; bad ſtewards of that time which thou haſt afforded us for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance &amp; good works, &amp; of thoſe talents which thou haſt committed to our improvement.</p>
               <p>If we put our hands into our boſomes, we muſt needs draw them out all leprous. For we are the brood of rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and diſobedient Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents:
<pb n="355" facs="tcp:35549:182"/>our hearts are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of unclean birds, of noiſome luſts; and the thoughts thereof have been evil, and only evill, and that continually.</p>
               <p>And if ô Lord we look forth unto the actions of our lives, there is no ſin which we have not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, no command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which we have not broken. Theſe eys which now look up unto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, have beheld vanity; theſe tongues which now call upon thee, have blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed thee; and theſe
<pb n="356" facs="tcp:35549:183"/>hands which we now lift up unto thee, have been many times lift up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, and thy Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes. So that we have made our ſelves unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the leaſt of thy mercies, but worthy of the greateſt of thy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But deal not with us after our ſins, neither reward us according to our iniquities.</p>
               <p>Spare us good Lord, ſpare thy people, whom thou haſt created after thine own Image, and redeemed with thine
<pb n="357" facs="tcp:35549:183"/>own Blood. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the multitude of thy tender compaſſions which have ever been of old to us, blot out the multitude of our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions. Pardon our ſins and receive us again un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy favour, for his ſake and ſufferings, who hath ſatisfied thy Juſtice to the utmoſt farthing.</p>
               <p>And for the ſhort re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue and remainder of our days, give us grace to conſecrate it to thy ſervice, to redeem that time which we cannot
<pb n="358" facs="tcp:35549:184"/>recall, and to make our calling and election ſure before we go hence, and be no more ſeen.</p>
               <p>And becauſe the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of our nature are too many, and too ſtrong for us, and the Divel like a roaring Lion goes about continually to devour us; leave us not to our ſelves, but aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt us by thy grace, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect thy ſtrength in our weakneſſe, and preſerve both our bodies and ſouls ſpotleſſe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable, that when we
<pb n="359" facs="tcp:35549:184"/>ſhall have finiſhed our courſe, and run the race of our naturall Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, we may receive that crown of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which thou the righteous and juſt Judg haſt laid up for all them that love and expect the day of thy appearing.</p>
               <p>And together with us we intreat thee for a bleſsing upon our <hi>King, Queen, Prince,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Roiall Progeny:</hi> upon our Councellors, Miniſters &amp; Magiſtrates: upon our friends, kinred,
<pb n="360" facs="tcp:35549:185"/>and acquaintance: upon the whole Church, and every afflicted member of it.</p>
               <p>And accept of our morning ſacrifice of praiſe, and thankſgiving for all the mercies and favours, comforts and deliverances which from time to time thou haſt afforded, and continued to us: We thank thee for thy laſt mercy in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving us from the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of this night paſt, for refreſhing our bodies with ſeaſonable reſt, and
<pb n="361" facs="tcp:35549:185"/>bringing us ſafe to the beginning of this day.</p>
               <p>Lord, what is man that thou art ſo mindfull of him, or the Son of man that thou ſhouldeſt thus viſit, &amp; remember him? Give us grace, O Lord, to remember thee, and to be mindfull of thy mercies, that we may praiſe thee for all the truth and faithfulneſſe which thou ſheweſt to us in the land of the living; that as thou haſt brought us to the comforts of this day, ſo thou mayeſt
<pb n="362" facs="tcp:35549:186"/>go along with us in the ſame, to enable us for the duties of thoſe callings wherein we are placed, and to deliver us from thoſe dangers to which we are expoſed, even for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, in whoſe moſt bleſſed name and words we conclude theſe our weak, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect prayers, ſaying as he himſelf hath taught us in his holy Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="363" facs="tcp:35549:186"/>
               <head>A PRAYER FOR the Evening.</head>
               <p>O Moſt glorious and ever living LORD God, which inhabiteſt eternity, and dwelleſt in that light which no mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall eye can attain unto; the God in whom we live, and move, and have our being; we thine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſervants do here in all lowlineſſe and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, preſent our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and prayers before thy divine Majeſty: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing &amp; acknowledging
<pb n="364" facs="tcp:35549:187"/>that we were conceived in ſin, and brought forth in iniquity; and, as if that had been but a ſmal mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, we have heaped up our actuall tranſgreſſions as the ſand upon the Sea ſhore, and as the ſtars in the firmament for num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. We have broken thy Commandements, we have prophaned thy Sabbaths, we have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured thy name, we have abuſed thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, we have neglected the day of our viſitation, &amp; turned thy grace into
<pb n="365" facs="tcp:35549:187"/>wantonneſs, whereby we have moſt juſtly provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thy wrath, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting diſpleaſure, we have wounded our own conſciences, weakned our aſſurance of ſalvation, &amp; grieved thy good Spirit, which ſealeth us up unto the day of our redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>And now Lord, if thou ſhouldeſt deal with us af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our deſervings, thou mighteſt pour upon us the deluge of thy wrath and fury to ſweep us out of the land of the living,
<pb n="366" facs="tcp:35549:188"/>into that place of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment prepared for the Divell and his Angels. But thou haſt revealed thy ſelf unto the ſons of men to be the Lord, the Lord, merciful and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, long ſuffering, and of great goodneſſe, one that pardons ſin, &amp; paſſes by the tranſgreſſions of thy people: this is thy name for ever, and thy memoriall throughout all generations.</p>
               <p>We appeal therefore from thee, unto thee, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the barof thy Juſtice, to
<pb n="367" facs="tcp:35549:188"/>the bowels of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, beſeeching thee even for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake to be merciful unto us in the free pardon and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of all the ſins that ever we have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt thee. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of his obedience for our diſobedience, of his righteouſneſs for our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, of his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings for all our ſins; waſh them away in his blood, nail them to his Croſſe, hide them in his wounds, and bury them in his grave, that they
<pb n="368" facs="tcp:35549:189"/>may never riſe up for our confuſion here, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation hereafter.</p>
               <p>And as we deſire thee to be unto as a father of mercy, ſo be unto us a GOD of conſolation, ſpeak peace unto our ſouls &amp; conſciences, and ſay unto us that thou art the God of our ſalvation.</p>
               <p>And for the time to come, give us grace to die daily unto ſin by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of thy Sons death, &amp; to riſe up to newneſs of life, by the power of his reſurrection; wean our
<pb n="369" facs="tcp:35549:189"/>hearts, &amp; take off our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections from the things of this world, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure but for a ſeaſon, and raiſe them up unto thoſe things which are at thy right hand for evermore. Inlighten the darkneſs of our underſtandings, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the ſtubborneſs of our wils, rectifie the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order of our affections, and bring into obedience whatſoever exalteth it ſelf againſt thy will, that at laſt we may come to be ſuch as thou wouldeſt have us.</p>
               <pb n="370" facs="tcp:35549:190"/>
               <p>Deliver us ô God from the temptations of the divel, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the allurements of the world, from the luſts of the fleſh, &amp; from the evil example of this crooked and perverſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration wherein we live, that we may run the race of thy commandements without turning to the right hand or to the left.</p>
               <p>And foraſmuch as the days of our pilgrimage are but few and evil, and theſe earthly tabernacles of our bodies muſt be diſſolved, give us grace
<pb n="371" facs="tcp:35549:190"/>to paſſe the time of our dwelling in thy fear, that we may depart hence in thy favour, whenſoever, whereſoever, or howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it ſhall pleaſe thee to call for us.</p>
               <p>And we entreat thee yet further to continue and inlarge thy bleſsings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Church, &amp; Land wherein we live, upon the perſon &amp; government of our King, upon the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berations of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, upon the patience &amp; long ſuffering of all thoſe who are afflicted with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="372" facs="tcp:35549:191"/>croſs or calamity: &amp; becauſe they are unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to receive new bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings that are not thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for thoſe they have already received; wee bleſſe and praiſe thee for all the mercies &amp; favours which thou haſt afforded us for our ſouls, or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; for this life or a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. We thank thee for our election, creation, vocation, juſtification, ſanctification in ſome meaſure, &amp; aſſured hope of glorification with thee in thy Kingdome.
<pb n="373" facs="tcp:35549:191"/>We thank thee for the peace of our Church, for the health of our bodies, for the plenty of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of our families.</p>
               <p>And now, holy Father, ſeeing the night is upon us, &amp; we are ready to take our reſt, into thy hands we commit our ſouls &amp; bodies, and all that we have, beſeeching thee which art the Keeper of Iſrael, that neither ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, nor ſlumbreth, to take care for us; for if thou protect us not, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
<pb n="374" facs="tcp:35549:192"/>wil devour us, yea we ſhall ſleep a perpetuall ſleep, &amp; never riſe up to praiſe thee. We pray thee therefore be good to us this night, defend us fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> danger, refreſh us with comfortable reſt, &amp; raiſe us up to glorifie thee in the duties of the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, that thou maiſt ſtill be our God, and we thy people. Hear us and graciouſly anſwer us in theſe our requeſts, and what elſe thou knoweſt needfull and expedient for us, and that for Jeſus
<pb n="375" facs="tcp:35549:192"/>Chriſt his ſake, in whoſe moſt bleſſed name, and words, we conclude theſe our imperfect prayers, ſaying as he himſelf hath taught us: <hi>Our Father &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou art in bed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend thy ſelf to God in the words of <hi>David:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will lay me down in peace, and take my reſt, for thou only, O Lord, makeſt me to dwell in ſafety, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.8.</p>
               <p>Conſider, and heare me O Lord my God, lighten mine eyes, leſt I
<pb n="376" facs="tcp:35549:193"/>ſleep the ſleep of death, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.3.</p>
               <p>So when thou lieſt down, thou ſhalt not be afraid: yea thou ſhalt lie down, and thy ſleep ſhall be ſweet, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.24.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Grace before meat.</head>
               <p>GOod Lord pardon &amp; forgive us all our ſins, which make us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of all thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, bleſs theſe thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to the uſe of our bodies, bleſs our bodies to the uſe of our ſouls, and bleſſe both our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="377" facs="tcp:35549:193"/>and ſouls to thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, for Chriſt his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Grace after meat.</head>
               <p>THou O God which haſt created us by thy power, preſerved us by thy providence, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed us by thy blood, and at this time fed us by thy good creatures, be bleſſed and praiſed now and evermore. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:35549:194"/>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> printed by <hi>Tho. Maxey</hi> for <hi>George Badger,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in S. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35549:194"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
